-=THE LAST FANTASY=-榮譽出品
本字幕僅供學習交流 嚴禁用於商業途徑
-=TLF字幕組=- 翻譯：eve 校對：eve
片名：《博物館奇妙夜2》
假設這是你的家 突然斷電 一片漆黑
What if this was your house? Power's out. Lights are dead.
你的小傢伙們被困在走廊盡頭的雙層床上 哭著大喊…
Your little ones in their bunk bed down the hall, crying out...
媽媽！爸爸！快來！我害怕！
Mommy! Daddy! Come quick! I'm scared!
- 你必須第一時間趕過去 - 來了寶貝！爸爸來了！
- You need to get there, and fast. - Coming, honey! Daddy's coming!
你需要一件防身的傢伙 但首先 你需要的是一個手電筒
You'll need a weapon. But first, you'll need a flashlight.
但你四週一片漆黑 你該怎麼辦？
But you're in the dark! What are you gonna do?
要怎麼找到手電筒？ 讓我來告訴你答案
How are you gonna find it? I'll tell you how.
夜光手電筒！
The Glow-in-the-Dark Flashlight!
沒錯 朋友們！ 我是戴利設備的拉瑞·戴利
That's right, folks! I'm Larry Daley of Daley Devices,
接下去的電視導購單元
and we're gonna spend the next paid-programing block
將令您終身難忘
rocking your world.
和我一起來的還有我的朋友
And I brought along a friend to do it.
女士們先生們 歡迎喬治·福爾曼
George Foreman, ladies and gentlemen!
棒極了 拉瑞 棒極了！ 大家說他是不是很棒
Fantastic, Larry, fantastic! Isn't he fantastic, America?
不過說真的 這一切都是真的嗎 僅僅兩年以前
But, seriously, isn't it true that just two years ago,
你還只是一名博物館夜班守衛
you were working as a night guard at some dusty museum?
沒錯 你是連續兩屆世界重量級拳王 喬治·福爾曼
That is true, two-time world heavyweight champ George Foreman.
而我只是一個小人物喬 拿著夜光手電筒懷揣著一個夢
I was just a regular Joe with a flashlight and a dream.
應該是小人物拉瑞
You mean a regular Larry.
但這不是開玩笑 如今你是戴利設備的首席執行官
But what's no joke is you're CEO of Daley Devices,
你的發明已經成了我們生活的必備品 比如超級大狗骨頭！
creator of such indispensable items as the Super Big Dog Bone!
- 你們喜歡嗎？ - 還有防丟失鑰匙圈！
- You like that one? - The Unlosable Key Ring!
哦 對 那個小栗子
Oh, yeah, that little chestnut!
而現在你又推出了最新發明 大家一起說！
And now your latest breakthrough... Say it with me, America!
夜光手電筒！
The Glow-in-the-Dark Flashlight!
家庭安防有保障 這堿O戴利設備 有什麼可以幫助您？
Whatever the household crisis, this is Daley Devices. Can I help you?
蒂娜 把這份文件還給斯圖爾特 他的計算能力糟透了
Tina, give this back to Stewart. I don't trust his math, okay?
- 那傢伙又打來了 - 又打來？
- That guy called again. - Again?
拉瑞！爆炸新聞！沃爾瑪同意和我們洽談了
Lar! Huge news! We got the Wal-Mart meeting.
- 不會吧！什麼時候？ - 三天後
- No! When? - Yeah. Three days.
好吧 好的 那我們有的好準備了
Okay, all right. We got a lot of work to do.
你有聽我說嗎？那可是沃爾瑪
Well, okay, did you just hear me say "Wal" and "Mart" together?
是！我知道 這是件大事！
Yeah! I know, it's huge.
那該慶賀一下啊
So just take a second to be happy about it.
好吧
All right.
你真是太掃興了
You're totally making fun of me.
今天全公司集體慶祝直到關門 怎麼樣？
No, let's hold off on the victory parade till we close, okay?
遵命
You got it.
- 他想約什麼時候見面？ - 禮拜五早上十點
- And when does he want to meet? - They want Friday morning, 10:00 a.m.
好吧 你知道該怎麼做 取消推廣會
Okay, then, you know what? Cancel that pitch
關於螺旋推進電鋸的那個 好嗎？
for the electric saw thing with the propeller, all right?
- 我得集中思想 - 好的
- I just want to focus on this. - Okay.
- 就這樣 - 我女兒的生日也泡湯了！
- Just this. - My daughter's birthday, canceled!
你可以先回去 我會呆到很晚 好嗎？
You can go home. I'm gonna be pretty late, okay.
是 老闆
Okay, boss.
嗨抱歉 未經許可不得入內！
Hello! Excuse me! Unauthorized personnel!
這不是我們的一夜成名先生嗎
If it isn't our very own Mr. Success Story.
來重遊故地嗎？ 好幾個月沒看到你了
Come for one of your nostalgia tours? I haven't seen you for a few months.
對 我一直很忙 這堳蝏穧^事？
Yeah, I've been busy. What's going on here?
發展 他們這樣告訴我的
Progress, so they tell me.
這是發展趨勢 自然歷史博物館 2.0版
The future. Behold, Natural History, version 2.0.
歡迎來到自然歷史博物館 這堹酮搢麭斨A活的歷史！
Welcome to The Museum of Natural History, where history comes to life!
站出來 問出你的問題
Step up, ask your question.
孩子們排好隊一個一個來
Then let the next little boy or girl have their turn.
好吧 你的出生地？
Okay, where were you born?
就在這 紐約市 二十大街
Right here in New York City, on Twentieth Street.
我生於1858年10月27日
October 27th, the year of our Lord 1858.
歷史 歷史 學習 學習
Blah, blah, blah. History, history. Learning, learning.
改變美國人民 一次一個孩子提問
Changing America, one child at a time.
很棒 這麼說你們打算增加一些這樣的互動展品？
That's great. So you're adding some new interactive exhibits?
不 戴利先生 不是增加 而是替換所有舊的展品
No, Mr. Daley, not adding. Replacing the old exhibits.
- 那舊展品放去哪堙H - 清理出去
- Where are they going? - Away.
這些垃圾都要被清走 模型 蠟像
We're getting rid of all this junk. The dioramas, the waxworks,
還有這些破爛的動物模型 比如這隻手骨嶙峋的猴子
even some of the shabbier animals, like this scrawny little monkey.
你手腳輕點 它是只僧帽猴
You should be careful. He's a capuchin.
它是個猴子
It's a monkey.
它是稀有品種 它叫僧帽猴 不是只普通猴子
He's a rare breed. He's a capuchin. He's not just a monkey.
猴子 它就叫猴子 幹嘛分的這麼細？
"Monkey", then. I said "monkey". Why be specific?
當你準備扔掉一隻猴子時 你不需要為它取個拉丁名吧
When you're throwing away a monkey, you don't need the Latin name.
你到底是扔掉它還是搬到別的地方？
Are you throwing him away or are you moving him?
你專管靈長垃圾嗎？ 算了吧 寶貝
What are you, the Primate Garbage Police? Let it go, baby.
- 這是誰的主意？ - 當然是我的
- Whose idea was this? - Me, of course.
這事我說了算 我和董事會
I'm in charge. Me and the board.
主要是董事會的意見
Mainly the board.
你管這麼多幹嘛？
Anyway, why do you care?
不是 人們愛這些展品
No, it's just that people love this stuff.
人們 戴利先生 永遠喜新厭舊
People, Mr. Daley, love "What's next?"
這你應該清楚 你不是也走了
You should know that. You left.
我的情況不一樣 我的生意剛剛起步
My situation changed. My business took off...
對 你成功了 如果我是夜班守衛 我也能
Yeah, you became a success. So would I, if I was a night guard.
那這些會被運到哪堙H
So where are these guys going?
聯邦檔案館的地下儲藏室
Deep storage. Federal Archives.
- 在哪兒？ - 華盛頓
- Where's that? - Washington, D.C.
史密森尼學會
The Smithsonian.
我們可以阻止他們的
There's got to be something that we can do.
沒用了！它們明天早上就會被運走 都結束了！
It's done! They leave tomorrow morning. It's over.
嗨 夥計 你好嗎？ 你這把老骨頭還好嗎？
Hey, buddy, how you doing? How you doing with all this?
想看看我給你帶什麼了？
You want what's in here?
猜猜我給你帶什麼？ 是一條繩子嗎？
You think I got something for you? You think I got a little rope?
你扯得過我嗎？
Think you're stronger than me, huh?
你就這點力氣嗎？
Is that all you got, huh?
勞倫斯！很高興見到你 孩子
Lawrence! Good to see you, lad!
我也是 泰德！
Yeah, you too, Teddy.
布魯克林的守護者回來了！
The Guardian of Brooklyn has returned!
嘿 阿克 聽著 麥克菲都告訴我了
Hey, Ahk. Look, McPhee told me what's going on around here.
- 我有個主意 - 真的
- I had no idea. - Indeed.
勞倫斯 你最後一次來這兒以後 發生了很多事
A lot has transpired, Lawrence, since your last visit.
俗話說…
One would say that...
- 稍等 - 忙人
- Just... - Cricket.
嘿 誰來幫把手！
Hey, Bocephus! Little help over here!
嘿
Hey.
嘿 夥計們 你們好嗎？
Hey, fellas. How you doing?
看看
Well, lookee here.
大人物親自來啦
If it ain't Mr. Big-in-the-Britches himself,
你正好趕上見我們最後一面
come back just in time to see us off!
傑德 我聽說了 聽著 我真的不知道事情會變成這樣
Yeah, Jed, I heard. Look, I don't even know how this happened.
是啊 你當然會覺得很奇怪
Yeah. Yeah, real mystery how this happened.
也許答案就在你手堥滬 嗡嗡作響的盒子
Maybe the answer's on that magic buzzing box there in your hand!
你不在這堣F 鐵人 所以事情才會變成這樣！
You weren't here, Gigantor! That's how it happened!
沒什麼可奇怪的！
Ain't no mystery!
事實是 拉瑞 他們開會的時候
The fact is, Larry, there's no one else here to speak on our behalf
沒人再為我們說話了
during business hours.
沒人 沒人 笨瓜 笨瓜
None, none, dum-dum.
嘿 夥計們！沒事的
Hey, guys! It's okay!
我明天一早就給董事會打電話好嗎？ 我會做彌補
I'll call the board in the morning, all right? I got some pull now.
我會處理好 我們都會沒事
I'll handle this. We're gonna be okay here.
我們？你聽見了嗎？ 還是我們在做白日夢 強尼？
"We"? Did you hear that? You hear Daydream Johnny?
自從你對我們撒手不管以後 你是你 我們是我們
There ain't been a "we" ever since you put us on the "pay no mind" list.
這真讓人心寒
And that's a cold place to be, boy.
拉瑞 悲劇已經發生
Larry, what's done is done.
即使輝煌的羅馬帝國也有滅亡的一天
Even the glory of Rome had to come to an end.
你能不能別用這種悲哀的眼神看著空氣
Would you please not look dramatically off into the middle distance
你這麼說 讓我更加痛苦
when you say that? It makes me feel worse.
我不知道你在說些什麼
I don't know what you're talking about.
你看什麼？你看什麼？ 我在這
Where are you looking? Where are you looking? I'm over here.
我只是在看著牆
Just a bit of wall.
聽著夥計們 也許事情沒那麼糟
Look, guys, maybe it won't be so bad.
對 你說的對
Yes, you make a good point.
我們只是要去史密森尼而已
But this is the Smithsonian we're talking about here.
德克斯特 你根本不懂
Dexter, you don't know that.
重點不是這個 鐵人 我們要被掃地出門了！
You're missing the point, Gigantor! They're shipping us out!
拉瑞 我知道你只是在安慰我們
Larry, I know you're trying to make us feel better.
我能看得出你在真誠的為我們著急
I can see that you're genuinely slightly bothered,
但今天也許是最後一次了
but it's never going to be the same.
我們所有人 聚在一起 在這
All of us here, together, in this place.
這埵A也不是家了
It ain't never gonna be home, boy.
傑迪戴亞 別這樣 勞倫斯
Jedediah, please! Lawrence,
這種情況下大家都容易激動
these are emotional times for all of us.
但這是我們作為一家人的最後一夜
But it is our last night as a family,
我不願意看著你們浪費時間自怨自艾
and I don't want to see it squandered in self-pity.
讓我們在這神聖大殿做最後一次遊行吧 誰願意來？
So who will join me for one final stroll through these hallowed halls?
- 你想去逛一圈嗎？ - 不
- Do you want to go for a walk? - No.
我只想自怨自艾
I'm just gonna squander it in self-pity.
親愛的 上馬吧
My dear, shall we?
一路平安 親愛的
Safe journey, my love.
嘿 德克斯特 要幫忙嗎？
Hey, Dexter, want some help there?
別這樣夥計 別鬧情緒好嗎？
Hey, come on, man. No hard feelings, all right?
都會過去的
It's gonna be fine.
天快亮了 勞倫斯
It's almost dawn, Lawrence.
是啊 那麼 你的木箱呢 泰德？
Yeah. So, where's your crate, Teddy?
我不和他們一起走 勞倫斯
I won't be making this journey, Lawrence.
我 雷克斯 還有其他一些簽名展品
It seems myself, Rexy, and a few of the signature exhibits
還要留下 暫時
will be staying here for now.
可是復活金牌不在了
Without the tablet?
事實上 勞倫斯
In truth, Lawrence,
阿卡曼拉的復活金牌 會和他一起留在這
Ahkmenrah's tablet will be remaining here with him.
什麼？
What?
復活金牌不能隨他們一起走了 我的朋友
They're going without the tablet, my friend.
這恐怕是他們的最後一夜了
I'm afraid this night is their last.
你沒告訴他們
You didn't tell them.
作為一個紳士 痛苦我們只會留給自己
Sometimes it's more noble to tell a small lie than deliver a painful truth.
- 你會沒事吧？ - 我會盡力
- Are you gonna be okay? - I shall do my best.
誰知道呢？
And who knows?
俗話說 塞翁失馬焉知非福
Sometimes the greatest change brings about even greater opportunity.
看看你 勞倫斯
Look at you, Lawrence.
你離開之後 生活發生了翻天覆地的變化
You left this place and created quite a life for yourself.
是啊 也許你說的對
Yeah, I guess so.
我的朋友 你要對自己有信心
I should hope you'd do more than guess, my friend.
你是大企業的老闆 一手掌握大權
You're a captain of industry. The world at your fingertips.
在我看來 你擁有了一切你想要的
It seems to me you have everything you wanted.
沒有 我自己知道
Yeah, no, I know.
不 你不懂 如果可以 孩子
No, you don't. If I may, lad,
請允許我給你一點建議
allow me to offer you one piece of advice.
獲得真正幸福的關鍵是…
The key to happiness, to true happiness, is...
稍等一下 我得…
Hang on one sec. I just gotta...
處理一下這宗和日本人的買賣
I got this Japanese deal.
哦 算了 我關機吧 對不起
No, okay, I'm turning this off. I'm sorry.
幸福的關鍵是？
The key to happiness?
再見 泰德
I'll see you, Teddy.
他們真的走了？ 你什麼忙都沒幫上？
So they're gone? There's nothing you can do?
我也想做點什麼夥計 告訴你 我已經竭盡所能了
I wish there was, man. I'm telling you, I tried everything.
我和麥克菲談了 給董事會打了電話
I talked to McPhee, I called the board,
但今天早上他們還是被運走了
but they shipped them out this morning.
好多吃的啊 老爸
This is a lot of food, Dad.
對 我公司的愛德今天要過來 我記得我告訴過你
Yeah. Ed from work's gonna come by. I thought I told you.
我們要討論一些工作上的事情
We just have to go over a couple of little work things.
- 那今晚你要工作？ - 以前我每晚都工作 記得嗎？
- So you're working tonight. - I used to work every night, remember?
那時你擁有全世界最酷的工作
That was when you had the coolest job in the world.
但是「酷」可支付不起你昂貴的吉他 和別的花銷
Yeah, well, "cool" doesn't pay for your Guitar God VI or whatever.
- 喂？ - 鐵人！是我 傑迪戴亞
- Hello? - Gigantor! It's me, Jedediah!
- 撐住！撐住！ - 傑德?
- Hold! Hold! - Jed?
決不投降！
Never surrender!
傑德 你們在幹嘛？ 你是怎麼撥通電話的？
Jed, what are you... How did you dial the phone?
說來話長 那個死猴子偷來了復活金牌
Long story! That brazen little monkey stole the tablet,
我們這堻ㄔ揭角@片了老兄！
and now we're in a world of hurt, boy!
- 出什麼事了？ - 卡門拉！
- What's going on? - Kahmunrah!
- 卡門拉？ - 阿卡曼拉的哥哥 他來了！
- Kahmunrah? - Ahkmenrah's big brother! He's here!
- 相信我 他是來者不善！ - 決不！
- And trust me, not a friendly! - Never!
我重複一遍 來者不善！
I repeat, not a friendly!
- 那是匈奴王的聲音嗎 傑德？ - 我不知道我們還能撐多久
- Is that Attila, Jed? - I don't know how much longer
- 不要！ - 傑德？你沒事吧？
- we can fight them off! No! - Jed? Are you okay?
- 放開我！救命！ - 嘿 傑德
- Let go of me! Help! - Hey, Jed.
- 放開我 放開 你放開我 救命啊！ - 傑德
- Let go! No, you let go of me! Help! - Jed?
怎麼了？
What was that about?
我不知道
I don't know.
快點 我要把你送到你媽那兒
Here, come on. Gonna drop you off at your mom's.
- 出什麼事了 老爸？ - 我會去弄清楚的
- What's going on, Dad? - I'm gonna go find out.
夥計 麥克菲說聯邦檔案館在史密森尼
Okay, buddy, McPhee said the Federal Archives are in the Smithsonian.
那我究竟要去哪塈銦H
Where exactly am I going?
問得好 老爸 史密森尼其實是19座不同的博物館
That's the thing, Dad. The Smithsonian is actually 19 different museums.
它們圍繞著國家廣場
They're laid out around the National Mall,
從國會大廈一直到林肯紀念碑
from the Capitol to the Lincoln Memorial.
那堶惜偵臕禱~都有 確實有很多特別酷的東西
They got everything there. There's actually some really cool stuff.
尼基 別扯別的 檔案館到底在哪座博物館
Nicky, please focus. Which museum are the Archives in?
不是博物館 而是地下
Not in, under.
從這堿搘戌據了整個史密森尼的地下空間
It looks like it runs underneath the entire Smithsonian.
那麼如果阿卡曼拉的復活金牌在那下面的話
So if Ahkmenrah's tablet is down there...
所有歷史人物都將重見天日
The biggest museum in the world is coming alive.
你打算怎麼辦 老爸？
What is exactly is your plan here, Dad?
- 這你別擔心 - 你根本沒有計劃是不是？
- Don't worry about it. - You have no plan, do you?
尼古拉斯 我有一個超級絕妙的計劃
Now, Nicholas, I have a very good, highly thought-out plan.
- 你沒有計劃 - 好吧 我沒有計劃
- You have no plan. - Yes, I have no plan.
我進去後再聯絡
I'll call you when I'm in.
給你 謝謝
Here you go. Thanks.
歡迎來到全世界最大的博物館
Welcome to the biggest museum in the world.
是啊 這像一場旅行
I know, right? It's a trip.
那些掛在天花板上的飛機怎麼樣？ 很神奇吧
How about these planes dangling from the ceilings, huh? Pretty weird.
不好意思打擾了 請問聯邦檔案館怎麼去？
Hi, excuse me. Could you tell me how to get to the Federal Archives?
如果你是一個有永久保存價值的檔案 就能進去了
Of course. Just be a historical document worthy of storing for all eternity.
開個玩笑 他不是檔案
I'm kidding. He's not a document.
抱歉 先生 檔案館在地下層 那堿O禁區
I'm sorry, sir, the Archives are underground, and they're a secure area.
真的？完全禁止入內嗎？ 好吧 謝謝
Really? Like, totally secure? Okay, thank you.
女士們先生們 博物館將在一小時後閉館
Ladies and gentlemen, the museum will be closing in one hour.
卡門拉
Kahmunrah.
嘿 你想幹嘛？
Hey! What are you doing?
- 嚴禁觸摸 - 不 我沒有想摸
- No touching. - No, I wasn't gonna touch it.
你已經產生「摸機」了 夥計
You're moving in with some I.T.T., bro.
- 摸機？ - 觸摸動機 朋友
- I.T. T? - That's "Intent to Touch", homey.
我沒有 我知道這不許碰…
No, I wasn't. You're not allowed to go over the...
- 怎麼 你還想親它嗎？ - 好吧 對不起
- What, are you gonna kiss it? - All right, sorry.
你手放上去碰一下試試 我站在那兒等上一天
Put your hand on it and touch it. 'Cause I stand there
就是等像你這樣想摸它的小女孩
and I wait all day for a little girl like you to come in
用她帶著光鮮亮麗指甲的手碰展品
and put her precious nail-polished nails all over the exhibits.
對不起 我以為我們生活在一個自由民主的國家…
Sorry. Last time I checked, I thought we lived in a free country, so...
- 不 不是 - 不是？
- No, we don't. - No?
這個國家規定你 不許碰你前面的這個東西
It's the United States of Don't Touch That Thing Right in Front of You.
我只是想… 在這兒站著看不犯法吧？
I just want to... I'm allowed to look at it here, okay?
你碰一下試試！
See what happens when you touch it!
你在威脅我嗎？ 你在威脅我嗎 布蘭頓
So you're threatening me? You're threatening me, Brandon?
- 是布倫頓 - 什麼？
- It's "Brundon." - Excuse me?
- 布倫頓 - 布倫頓？
- "Brundon"! - "Brundon"?
- 布倫頓 - 布倫頓
- "Brundon." - "Brundon."
好像印你的胸卡時他們丟了個字母
What, did they run out of U's on your nameplate maker?
不知道 你媽是不是沒教過你
I don't know, did they run out of jokes
什麼時候該開玩笑？
at the interesting-joke store that you shop at?
不好意思 看上去像是布蘭頓…
Sorry, it looks like "Brandon", but...
我不是來教你語音的 是布倫頓
I'm not here to be your speech therapist. It's "Brundon"!
- 布倫頓 好的… - 你以前沒聽說過這名字嗎？
- "Brundon." Okay... - You never heard of the name before?
布倫頓？沒有
"Brundon"? No.
1984年最流行的名字 布倫頓
Look up most popular baby names in 1984. "Brundon."
好吧 你在威脅我嗎 布倫頓？
Okay. Are you threatening me, Brundon?
我不知道 茉莉公主 我有嗎？
I don't know, Princess Jasmine. Am I?
- 哇 月光九號手電筒 - 沒錯
- Oh, wow. Lunabeam nine-volt. - Yeah.
硬體不錯啊
Wonderful piece of hardware, huh?
- 商標在這兒 月光九號 - 太好了
- That's their title, Lunabeam Nine. - Great.
我個人更偏愛美光手電筒
I prefer the Maglite LED myself, but that's just me.
- 幫我個大忙 - 什麼忙？
- Do me a huge favor. - What?
把手放回褲帶 放低你的姿態
Shove your hands into your pockets, put your attitude way down,
還有 對人友好些
and, also, be nice to people.
我能再問你一個問題嗎？
Great. But could I just ask you one thing?
- 可以 - 我只想弄清楚
- Yeah. - Okay, so just to be clear,
- 我不能碰它 對嗎？ - 好吧 你這個瘋子
- so, I can't do this, right? - Okay, that's actually crazy.
你想找死嗎？
Did you just make a decision to possibly end your life
你活得不耐煩了吧？
earlier than you were expecting?
我會用手電筒打你
I'm gonna hit you with the flashlight.
- 你在威脅我 - 別碰它！
- Now you are threatening me. Okay. - Do not touch it!
- 別碰我！ - 你別碰它！
- Don't touch me. - Do not touch it!
- 別碰它！ - 你別碰我！
- Do not touch it! - Don't touch me!
我想怎麼碰你就怎麼碰你
I'll touch you with my flashlight all day.
不 你的手電筒是用來照明的
No, your flashlight is meant to illuminate.
我打個比方 我們去露營
I will literally rent a camper,
開著車橫跨美國 一路上我都要拿手電筒碰你
and we will drive across America with my flashlight on your chest.
- 你別這樣 - 別怎樣？
- Don't do that. - Don't do what?
我就碰了你了怎麼樣？
Want to see what happens when I do it one more time?
- 你等著瞧 - 瞧什麼瞧
- Let's see what happens. - Watch you do nothing.
瞧你傻站在那兒嗎
Let's watch you do nothing when I do this.
說真的 布蘭頓…
Seriously, Brandon...
- 布倫頓 - 布倫頓
- Brundon. - Brundon,
你知道我是誰嗎？
you do not know who you're dealing with.
你知道當守衛意味著什麼嗎？
You think you know what it means to be a guard, huh?
相信我 你根本不懂守衛的含義
Trust me, you don't know the meaning of the word.
我見過的東西你連想都不敢想
I have seen things that you could not imagine.
- 比如什麼？ - 我不會告訴你
- Like what kind of stuff? - I'm not gonna tell you.
- 但是你得放下手電筒… - 你這麼說
- But you're gonna drop the flashlight... - The way you said it,
聽上去你有什麼很有意思的事
it sounded like you were gonna say something cool.
對 可惜你聽不到
Yeah, well, you don't get to hear it.
放下手電筒
Drop the flashlight.
沒事了吧？
We cool?
你剛才真是太酷了
That's actually pretty cool, what you just did.
謝謝
Thank you.
別記恨我好嗎?
No hard feelings?
- 好嗎？對不起 - 沒事
- All right? Sorry. - Okay.
- 我很抱歉 - 不 是我的錯 我不應該…
- I'm sorry. - No, It's my fault. I shouldn't have...
不 一個巴掌拍不響 再說…
No. It takes two opposing forces to cause friction, and...
你只是在盡你的本職 沒事的
And you're just doing your job, all right.
- 放鬆點 夥計 - 好的！
- Take it easy, man. - Yeah!
那傢伙真酷
That guy's great.
好了 夥計 我進去了
Okay, buddy, I'm in.
太棒了 告訴我你現在的位置
Great. Where are you?
城堡的東北角走廊 剛出國會
The northeast corridor of the Castle, just off the Commons.
- 帶我到檔案館 - 好的
- I need you to talk me to the Archives. - Okay.
到走廊盡頭 右轉
At the end of the hall, turn right,
在你左手邊可以看到一個樓梯間
and there should be a stairwell coming up on your left.
- 明白 - 這下面像個迷宮
- Got it. - Now, it's kind of a maze down there.
地下通道把不同建築連成一體
Those underground tunnels connect a bunch of different buildings.
- 地形非常複雜 - 我們沒時間了
- It could get complicated. - We'd better hurry,
還有28分鐘太陽就落山了
we only got 28 minutes till sundown.
下到B層以後 再一次左轉
When you get down to B level, you want to take another left...
- 尼克 喂 尼克？ - 老爸！聽得見嗎…
- Nick? Hello? Nick? - Dad! Can you hear...
尼克 你說…尼克？
Nick, you're... Nick!
- 身份 布倫頓 - 嘿
- ID, Brundon. - Hey.
- 你晚了 老兄 - 是啊
- Later, dude. - All right. Yeah.
好了 大夥兒都在哪兒？
All right. Where are you guys?
哦 上帝
Oh, my God.
你這個搗蛋鬼 我一會兒再找你算賬
You little troublemaker. I'm gonna deal with you later.
不 不 不 不 不！
No. No! No, no, no!
英語 英語會說嗎？
No, English. English, perhaps.
抱歉 你是誰？
I'm sorry, who are you?
我是卡門拉 我是王中之王
I am Kahmunrah, the great king of the great kings,
從最黑暗的古老歷史深處
and from the darkest depths of ancient history,
我死而復生！
I have come back to life!
你大概沒聽清我的話
Perhaps you did not hear what I just said.
我是古老埃及的法老 我曾經死去
I am a centuries-old Egyptian Pharaoh. I was dead,
但是現在 我死而復生！
but now I have come back to life!
哦 是 我聽清了 我明白你的意思 歡迎回來！
Yeah, no. I heard that. I got that. Welcome back.
- 你是誰？ - 戴利設備的拉瑞·戴利
- Who are you? - Larry Daley. Daley Devices?
我公司在紐約市 很有趣 我還認識你弟弟阿卡曼拉
It's up in New York. It's funny, I know your brother, Ahkmenrah.
- 是嗎？ - 是的
- Do you? - Yeah.
他說他認識我弟弟 最受寵的兒子
He knows baby brother. The favorite son.
- 對 是個好孩子 - 誰說不是呢？
- Yeah, good kid. - Isn't he just?
知道嗎 媽媽和爸爸總是把所有最好的給他
You know, Mother and Father always gave him the best of everything,
我說的是所有 甚至包括王位
and I do mean everything. They even gave him the throne.
我才應該是王位繼承人！
The throne which was rightfully mine!
- 他沒提過這事 - 我打賭他不會說
- He never mentioned that. - I'll just bet he didn't.
不過卡門拉時代現在來臨了 因為我死而復…
Well, now begins the era of Kahmunrah, because I have come back to...
算了 把金牌給我
Never mind, just hand me the tablet.
別給他 鐵人！
- Don't give it to him, Gigantor! - Keep him away!
安靜！你們給我安靜！
Silence! Silence in there, please!
- 別逼我進去！ - 我不會保持沉默！
- Don't make me come in there! - No! I won't be muzzled!
聽著 這金牌所擁有的力量
Look, that tablet is more powerful
是你這個戴利設備的拉瑞·戴利 根本無法想像的
than you, Larry Daley of Daley Devices, can possibly imagine.
恢復生命只是其中一個小把戲
Bringing things back to life is just a parlor trick.
有了它 我就可以開啟塵封的地下世界之門
With it, I shall unlock the Gate to the Underworld
從死亡之地召回我的軍隊
and bring forth my army from the Land of the Dead.
如果不麻煩的話…
So, if it's not too much trouble...
…把它給我
...hand it over.
好吧 給你
Okay, here you go.
明智的選擇
Wise decision.
是啊 很抱歉 我以為你是想要那個魔方 不過…
Yeah, I know. I'm sorry, I thought you wanted the Cube, but...
魔方？
The Cube?
魔法立方體
The Cube of Rubik.
好吧 這個魔法立方體是幹什麼的？
All right, what is this Cube of Rubik, then?
就是魔方 那個可以把你的敵人化成灰的魔方
The Cube. You know, the one that turns all who oppose you to dust?
有這個玩意兒嗎？隨便吧 總之…
That one? Whatever. I thought...
是我不好 順便說一句
It was my bad, 'cause... You know what? By the way,
你弟弟也不想搞得這麼砸
your brother didn't want to mess with it, either.
他不想兩敗俱傷
Yeah, he wanted to play it safe, too.
只是 你看上去像比他厲害些 所以我…
Just, you sort of struck me as a next-level sort of guy, so I was...
我不是我弟弟 拉瑞
I am not my brother, Larry.
只需一眨眼的功夫 我就能殺光你和你的朋友們
I will kill you and your friends in the blink of an eye.
帶我去那個魔法立方體
Now take me to this Cube of Rubik.
- 就在這兒 - 打開
- Here it is. - Open it.
回來！把金牌還給我！
Come back here! Come back here with my tablet!
你朋友還在我手上！
I still have your friends!
- 你來開！ - 什麼？
- Take the wheel! - What?
我說你來開 打起來了 打起來了 我愛它
I said, take the wheel! Oh, we're in it now! I love it! I love it!
筆直往前 其他我來對付
Just keep her straight, I'll handle the rest.
前進！
Now, charge!
好吧 接下去你有什麼計劃？
Okay, so what's the plan here?
我們是美國人！我們從不計劃 我們是行動家！
We're Americans! We don't plan, we do!
不要減速！
Now hold on!
看到沒有？先行而後思 每次都管用！
See that? Act first, think later! Works every time!
我可是好手！
You're in good hands!
美國第七騎兵隊將軍 喬治·阿姆斯特朗·卡斯特
General George A. Custer of the Fighting U.S. 7th Cavalry,
為您效勞
at your service.
我沒事 繼續開 笨蛋
I'm good, I'm good! Fly, you fool!
你們吵什麼吵 牛仔？
What's the rumpus, ace?
聽著 女士 你能讓開嗎？
Look, lady, could you get out of the way?
女士？你叫誰女士？ 我是阿梅莉亞
Lady? Who are you calling lady? The name is Amelia.
阿梅莉亞·埃爾哈特 我想你聽說過我吧
Amelia Earhart! Perhaps you've heard of me?
哦 是啊 著名飛行員什麼的吧
Oh, right. You're a famous pilot or whatever.
飛行員？ 我可是第一個飛越大西洋的女性
Pilot? I was the first woman to fly the Atlantic!
第一個榮獲飛行十字勳章的女性
First woman to receive the Flying Cross,
第一個駕駛自轉旋翼機 飛越美國48個州的女飛行員
first woman to fly across the 48 states in a gyroprop.
如果你願意的話請先放下你那副永遠緊張兮兮的嘴臉
Now if you'd wipe that perhaps-permanent look of alarm off your kisser,
請告訴我我現在在哪兒 非常感謝
I was wondering if you might be so kind as to tell me exactly where I am.
你在一個博物館 準確點是博物館下面
You're in a museum. Or, actually, under it.
我現在是眾矢之的
And I'm in kind of a dangerous situation right now,
所以你最好躲到離我遠點的地方
so you might not want to be anywhere near me.
- 你動作真快 - 你叫什麼 飛行員？
- Wow, you're fast. - What's your name, flyboy?
我叫拉瑞·戴利
My name is Larry Daley.
拉瑞·戴利 你給我聽好了
Well, Larry Daley, in case you weren't listening,
我可不是個膽小怕事的人
I'm not one to shy away from danger.
那矛呢 你怕不怕矛呢？
How about spears? Are you one to shy away from spears?
讓我們找點樂子 機長！ 痛快玩一場吧
Let's ankle, skipper! Now we're gonna have some fun.
98 99 完美
Ninety-eight, ninety-nine, bingo!
像金羊毛一樣
Like a Golden Fleece.
聽著 士兵們 當你們的敵人抓住我的時候
All right, troops, when your enemies captured me,
他們也就成了我的甕中之鱉
they made themselves my enemies as well.
大錯誤 一個大錯誤
Big mistake. Big mistake.
我的計劃是這樣的
All right, here's the plan.
吹響三聲號角 我會大聲宣佈：「攻擊！」
On the third bugle blast, I shall loudly announce, "Attack!"
然後我們全體跳出這個箱子
At which point, we will all jump out of this box
開始攻擊
and attack.
很震撼吧 覺得怎麼樣？
Mind bomb. What do you think?
你說 薩什麼什麼…
You, Sacaja...
那不是我的名字
That is not my name.
- 薩卡婭米爾 - 不是
- Sacajamea. - No.
- 變態 娘娘腔（俚語） - 不是
- Sack-in-a-box. - No.
（西班牙文5月5日 一個節日）
Cinco de Mayo.
我知道你是個著名的將軍…
I know you are a famous general...
那算不上什麼 我也是個普通人 和你一樣
That's all right, that's all right. I'm a person, just like you.
當你大叫「攻擊」的時候
But won't yelling, "Attack!" Alert the enemy
敵人不就立刻知道我們要攻擊了嗎？
that we are about to attack?
什麼？
What?
哦 也許你說的對
Yeah, I guess so.
你很受歡迎嘛 戴利先生
You're quite the popular fellow, Mr. Daley.
你幹嘛不直接逃走？
Why don't you just skedaddle?
我不能逃 我的朋友還在他們手上
I can't skedaddle. My friends are being held down there.
我得去救他們 得另找一條路下去
I got to go get them. I got to find another way down.
以前沒見過
This is new.
沒事 我不會傷害你們
Hey, it's all right. I don't want to hurt you.
我想他們怕的不是你 戴利先生
I don't think it's you they're afraid of, Mr. Daley.
交換 謝謝
Trade you. Thanks.
退後 給我退後！
Back off! Just back off!
小心被我叉到
I will fork you!
別輕舉妄動
How about you, huh?
男人就是不如女人
Never send a boy to do a woman's job.
我曾用兩個星期的時間在密克羅尼西亞群島和土著學習用矛
I spent two weeks spear-hunting with a tribe in Micronesia.
密克羅尼西亞人的反應沒這麼快
The Micronesians had much slower reflexes.
走
Come on!
戰爭結束了！戰爭結束了！
It's over! It's over! It's all over!
這兒可真是熱鬧啊
Well, this is one humdinger of a hootenanny.
讓一下 不好意思 讓一讓
Excuse me. Sorry. Excuse me.
哇 1945年的信號這麼強
Wow, four bars in 1945.
- 喂？ - 老爸 總算通了！
- Hello? - Dad, finally!
我一直在研究檔案館地形
I've been studying these plans to the Archives.
一旦你下了樓梯…
Looks like once you get down the stairwell...
哦 我早就下了樓梯了 尼基
Oh, I'm way past the stairwell, Nicky.
- 這麼說你找到大家了？ - 算是吧
- So you found everyone? - Sort of.
你在對著什麼東西講話？
What is that flibberty-widget you are talking to?
- 那是誰？ - 阿梅莉亞·埃爾哈特
- Who's that? - It's Amelia Earhart.
你找到了阿梅莉亞·埃爾哈特？
You found Amelia Earhart?
我…嘿！
I... Hey!
- 等會兒！ - 老兄 你急什麼啊！
- Wait a minute! - Buddy, what's your hurry?
你沒聽到嗎？戰爭結束啦！
Didn't you hear? The war's over!
抱歉 那些人在追我
Sorry. These guys are chasing me.
什麼？都是些什麼人啊 狂歡節表演嗎？
What? What am I looking at, Mardi Gras?
- 你是哪堥茠滿H - 布魯克林
- What unit are you from? - I'm from Brooklyn.
你說真的？ 我是弗萊巴許的 嘿 兄弟們
What? Are you serious? I'm from Flatbush! Hey, fellas!
那些怪人要打我兄弟
These so-and-so's are trying to rough up my pal here
就因為他是布魯克林的
just 'cause he's from Brooklyn!
- 謝謝 - 別客氣 給我打！
- Thank you! - You got it! Fight!
嘿 先生！你忘了東西…
Hey, mister! You forgot your...
這是什麼玩意兒？ （請注意片尾曲中有相關情節）
What the heck is this thing?
對不起 把她借我一會兒行嗎？
Excuse me. Mind if I get in here?
你吻完沒有 戴利先生
Any time you're done, Mr. Daley.
- 給我打電話！ - 謝謝你
- Call me! - Thank you for that.
你對付女人挺有一套啊 戴利先生
So you're quite the smooth operator, aren't you, Mr. Daley?
快！
Quick!
- 終於擋住了 - 接下去幹嘛？
- That actually worked. - What's next?
聽著 我不是針對你 不過我現在正處於水深火熱中
Look, nothing personal, but I'm kind of in the middle of something here
這可不是你開飛機這麼簡單
that's not really your fight.
就因為我是個女人 對不對？
It's because I'm a woman, isn't it?
不 因為有個死而復生的邪惡法老
No, it's because I've got this ancient raised-from-the-dead evil Pharaoh guy
要我手上這塊石板 他會殺了我甚至我身邊的任何一個人
who's willing to kill me and probably anyone near me to get this tablet
有了石板他就能統治世界
so he can rule the world.
所以說還是因為我是女人！
So it is because I'm a woman!
- 聽著 我… - 不 你給我聽著 戴利先生！
- Look, I... - No, you look, Mr. Daley!
要不是我把你拉出來了 你現在還陷在那個黑白鬧劇中
If it weren't for me, you'd still be lost in that monochromatic mayhem!
- 陷在什麼中？ - 那張黑白照片 蠢貨
- Lost in what? - Black and white photo, you boob!
聽著 聽好了 我想幫你
Now listen, and listen good. I can help you.
我想幫你 不是因為我喜歡你 我才不喜歡你
I want to help you, and not because I like you, which so far I don't,
而是因為我聞到了冒險的味道 見鬼 我要加入你
but because I smell adventure, and, damn it, I want in.
好吧 出了事可別怪我
Okay. Don't blame me if something happens to you.
我的命長著呢
I should be so lucky.
我是卡門拉 我是半個神
I am Kahmunrah. I am half god,
從我出生開始
once removed on my mother's side,
我就是埃及王國的合法繼承人 將來也要統治…
rightful ruler of Egypt, future ruler of...
所有一切
Well, everything else.
我損失了一些人
Now, I have lost some men.
所以現在我需要一些幫手
So, I am in need of some new generals to join me in my little plan
和我一起征服世界
of conquering this world.
恐怖的伊凡
Ivan the Terrible.
拿破侖·波拿巴
Napoleon Bonaparte.
還有年輕的艾爾·卡彭
And young Al Capone.
是的
Yeah.
你們都是歷史上數一數二的大壞蛋
Some of the most despicable, most feared leaders in all of history.
先生們
Gentlemen,
真的 我真想不到能見到你們
really, it's just fantastic to meet you all.
- 我們也是 - 我也是
- And us, too. - And me, you.
只要你們衷心於我 我承諾你們的是整個世界
All I ask is your allegiance, and in return, I offer you the world.
你們有什麼問題嗎？
Literally. Are there any questions?
我有一個問題 你怎麼會穿著裙子？
Yeah, I got one. How come you're wearing a dress?
這不是裙子 這叫做袍子
This is not a dress. This is a tunic.
3000年前很流行的 我告訴你
It was the height of fashion 3,000 years ago, I assure you.
還有別的問題嗎？
Are there any other questions?
有 你穿的這個裙子
Da. This dress you're wearing,
我們也要穿嗎？
do we have to wear one of these, too?
你剛才沒在聽嗎？ 我已經回答了卡彭先生的問題
Were you not listening? I just told Mr. Capone here
這不是裙子
that this is not a dress.
事實上 這是件袍子 區別很大的
It is, in fact, a tunic. Very big difference.
還有問題嗎？
Are there any other questions?
還有別的與裙子無關的問題嗎？
Any questions not about the dress?
袍子
Tunic?
那麼好吧 不要浪費月色了
All right, then. Moonlight is wasting,
- 我們時間很短 - 短？
- and the time is short. - Short?
為什麼你說「短」的時候要看著我？
Why do you look at me when you say "short"?
對不起 我無意的
Sorry. It slipped out.
好吧 如果你說的是征服世界
Da. If we are talking about world domination,
那我當然有興趣
then of course, I am interested.
不過我想先澄清一件事情 你得搞清楚你在和誰合作
But first I want to clarify something so you know what you are getting.
人們總是說：伊凡很恐怖 他很嚇人
People always say, "Ivan the Terrible, he's so terrible.
我很怕伊凡 他是個惡棍
"I'm so scared of Ivan. He's bad news."
其實正確的翻譯應該是
When in fact, the correct translation is
令人畏懼的伊凡
"Ivan the Awesome".
令人畏懼的伊凡？
Ivan the Awesome?
那個比較難記 不是嗎？
It's not really as catchy, is it?
我是說 恐怖的伊凡更容易記
I mean, "Ivan the Terrible", that really pops.
可是我一點都不恐怖 事實上我是個很能幹的領袖
But I wasn't terrible. In fact, I was quite an effective leader.
好我記住了 現在我想用一個問題來結束
Duly noted. Now, I'd like to wrap up the old meet-and-greet
今晚的面談會
by asking you gentlemen a question.
你們跟不跟我？
Are you with me?
- 跟 跟 - 跟
- Yeah. Yeah, sure. - Oui.
- 我跟 不過… - 那就把戴利設備的拉瑞·戴利
- Da, but... - Then bring Larry Daley of Daley Devices
還有阿卡曼拉的復活金牌弄來給我！
and the Golden Tablet of Ahkmenrah to me!
我帶你下去找你的朋友 戴利先生
We'll get you back down to your chums, Mr. Daley.
跟著阿梅莉亞·埃爾哈特 你絕對不會迷路
You won't get lost following Amelia Earhart.
快點 蹲下
Quick, get down.
戴利先生 我很喜歡你這麼摟著我
Well, well, Mr. Daley, I quite like the way you're holding me.
對不起 我不是那個意思…
No. Sorry, I wasn't trying to...
拜託你戴利先生 別嘟嘟囔囔的
Oh, please, stop beating your gums, Mr. Daley.
自打你看到我那刻起
You haven't been able to take your cheaters off my chassis
你的眼睛就沒離開過我的飛機底盤
since the moment we met.
你說的話我全部聽不懂
I literally didn't understand one word of that.
是我聽錯了還是有人在唱歌？
Is it just me or is there music in the air?
# …寶貝 我們可以使其閃耀 我們能夠保持永遠… #
# ... my baby, we can make it shine We can take forever... #
你們 會飛的小天使 安靜！
You! Little flying angel things! Quiet!
他們是丘比特 戴利先生 是愛神
They're cupids, Mr. Daley. Gods of love.
太棒了 愛神 你們能閉嘴嗎？ 閉嘴 我們會暴露的
Great. Gods of love, would you shut up? Please shut up. We're trying to hide.
# 耶！特別的女人 耶！#
# Yeah! More than a woman! Yeah! #
別換了 不是編曲的問題 給我安靜！
No, don't change the arrangement, it's not about the arrangement. Quiet!
大家一起唱！
Kick the chorus, y'all!
特別的女人
More than a woman
讓我看看你的能耐 守衛！
Yo, show me what you got, night guard!
快點 我們走
All right, come on. Let's go.
# 對我來說是一個特別的女人 #
# More than a woman to me #
# 一個特別的女人 #
# More than a woman #
# 她是個特別的女人 #
# She's more than a woman #
你這隻小到不能再小的小老鼠
And so, the little tiny man who could not be a smaller or shorter mouse
自動跑到大貓咪的面前
runs into the claws of the giant cat!
你真的這麼在乎高度啊
You're really hung up on the height, aren't you?
- 我根本不在乎高度… - 不 你在乎
- No, it's not about height, see... - Yes, you are.
你的意思是我只是一隻小老鼠 而你是一隻大貓咪
You're saying I'm a little mouse, you're a giant cat.
- 我是大貓咪 - 我並不想冒犯你 不過…
- I am the giant cat. - No offense, I just...
你是拿破侖 你擁有很多很多的形容詞
You're Napoleon. There's a complex named after you.
矮就是其中之一 真的 你自己看看
You're famous for being little, and it's true. Look.
哦 你這個幼稚的美國男孩
Oh, you naive American man-boy.
聽著 現在討論這個很無聊好嗎
Look. Neither of us are gonna be jamming anytime soon, right?
我們不該浪費時間… 在這個不值一提的問題上
So it's not like we should... It's not even an issue.
人不是以高矮來評價的 是頭腦 一個偉大的頭腦
It's not about height or something else. It's a plan. It's a brilliant plan.
- 你是很有頭腦 - 說的好 皇帝先生
- So it was a plan. - Snazzy maneuver, Emperor.
謝謝 小姐
Merci, mademoiselle.
如果你的男朋友能合作點 跟我走…
Now, if your boyfriend would kindly come with me...
我不是她男朋友
I'm not her boyfriend.
- 不是男朋友 - 不是
- Not her boyfriend. - No.
普通朋友？
Just friends?
- 是 普通朋友 - 只是認識而已 普通朋友
- Yeah, friends. - Acquaintances. Friends.
你們的關係 是不是類似那種大學同學
Were you guys, like, friends in college
相互暗戀 想要更進一步發展
and just afraid now to both ruin your relationship
但卻不敢告訴對方
by telling the other person that you want to be more than friends,
怕毀了你們現在的關係？
that you like-like each other?
再說一遍好嗎 抱歉 我沒聽明白…
One more time? I'm sorry. I didn't catch the...
你們的關係 是不是類似那種大學同學
Were you guys, like, friends in college
相互暗戀 想更進一步發展
and now both afraid to ruin your relationship
但卻不敢告訴對方
by telling the other person that you want to be more than friends,
怕毀了你們現在的關係？
that you like-like each other?
- 不是 - 不是？
- No. - No?
我喜歡挖掘兩性關係的本質 這是法國人的愛好
I just love the nitty-gritty of relationships. All us French do.
- 太好了 - 是啊 愛情
- Great. - Yes. Amour!
行了
- Now. - Yeah?
- 跟我走 要不就殺了你 - 遵命
- This way, or you die. - Yes.
- 等等 我也去 - 不！這事與你無關
- Wait, I'm coming with you! - No! Our fight is not with you.
…你還得再下一次注 - 好 好吧
...so you gotta bet a second time. - All right. Okay.
我的髮型在歐洲一帶流通很廣
My hair is currency in certain parts of Europe.
真的 流通很廣 就像黃金和錢
It's true. Currency, like gold or paper money.
一小盒能買下整個大教堂
The Duomo was purchased with just one locket.
聽著 朋友
Listen up, kemosabe.
這個馬戲團小丑 連煎餅和蒼蠅拍都分不清
This rodeo clown wouldn't know a flapjack from a flyswatter.
現在鐵人正在外面為我們拚命
Now, Gigantor's out there risking his hide for us.
至少我們要幫他一把
The least we can do is give him some help.
我們能幫大忙 但是在這塈丰H待斃就什麼忙也幫不上
Some big help. But we can't very well do that if we're stuck in here, now, can we?
我們得逃出去
We need to escape.
煎餅是什麼東西？
What's a flapjack?
類似一種餅乾或者麵包的東西
It's like a biscuit or a scone.
- 碰胸 - 好的
- Chest bump? - Yeah.
你玩完了 看牌
Then deadly. Watch.
看好你的牌 現在下注吧
Guard your cards, okay? Now you bet.
現在你得丟點牌下來
Okay, now you got to throw some cards down.
- 準備好了？ - 準備好了
- Ready? - Ready.
說點什麼 說點什麼 這不好玩 你必須…
Say something. Say anything. This is no fun. You're supposed to...
- 嘿 你們倆想幹嘛？ - 奧克塔維厄斯 跑！
- Hey! What are you two doing out here? - Octavius, go!
- 你 快跑 我掩護你 - 我不會一個人跑的
- You, make a run for it, I'll hold them off! - I will not leave you!
現在不是演羅馬連續劇 快跑 馬上！
Ain't no time for your Roman melodrama! Now, get! Go!
老傑迪戴亞不會有事
Old Jedediah will be fine.
好了 你麻煩大了
Now, you're in real trouble.
這些根本不是真的紅寶石
Why, these aren't real rubies at all.
真品紅寶石鞋
Ruby slippers indeed.
但是 不管你是誰 Archie Bunker
（為美國著名電視劇四海一家的主角）
But, whoever you are, Archie Bunker,
但這椅子坐的可真舒服
you had one comfortable throne.
老大
Hey, boss.
這傢伙從箱子的一個蚻}堸k出來 給我們抓住了
Caught this one trying to escape through a rust hole in the crate.
還有一個跑了
One of his little friends got away.
拜託 他們能幹得了什麼？
Oh, please. What damage could they possibly do?
看看 他們小的好像一粒米 是不是？
Why, they're no bigger than a little grain of couscous. Aren't you?
聽你說話我想到了兩個詞
You know, two words come to mind when I hear you talk.
神經病 精神分裂
"Delusional" and "weirdo".
如果還要說第三個詞的話 那就是「蠢豬」
And if I had to say a third, "goofy". Just goofy.
你快把老傑迪戴亞放出來 不然他可要發火了
Now you let old Jedediah out of here or he's gonna get angry.
說的好 傑迪戴亞
Well played, Jedediah!
對不起 我實在認真不起來 你太可愛了
I'm sorry, I can't take you seriously. You're just adorable,
連你威脅我的樣子也有趣極了
even when you're threatening me. It's hilarious.
是我的問題 還是這些小傢伙真是可愛的要命
Is it just me, or are these guys unbelievably cute?
你給我省省吧
Now hold it a second, now.
你可以囚禁我 甚至折磨我
Now, you have a right to keep me as your captive, torture me, even,
但不許說我可愛 我不可愛！
but don't call me cute! I ain't cute!
撐住 我的朋友！ 堅持住 我會救你出去！
Steady, my friend! Just stay alive! I will find you!
鐵人 不！
Gigantor. No!
你好 戴利先生 很高興再一次見到你
Hello, Mr. Daley. Nice to see you again.
如果你不介意的話 這個我要拿走了
Now, if you don't mind, I shall take that from you.
謝謝
Thank you.
終於！過了整整3000年
Finally. Finally! After 3,000 years,
我被詛咒的黑暗軍團 我可愛的軍團
my evil army of the damned, my beautiful, beautiful army,
將重見天日！
shall be unleashed!
我恐怕媽媽和爸爸
I'm afraid that Mother and Father may have
背著我稍稍改了一下密碼
slightly changed the combination on me.
這麼說地下怪物重見天日這套
I guess this whole unleashing-the-underworld thing
行不通了 對吧？
isn't really working out for you, huh?
你一定很難過吧 畢竟你都等了幾千年了
It must be really frustrating, 'cause you've waited thousands of years
好不容易死而復生
to come back from the dead and everything,
卻打不開地獄之門
and now you can't get it open.
我不怕 有必要的話我還可以再等上一千年
Fear not, for I shall wait a thousand more if I must.
很好 不過再過幾個小時你就會 變成一尊沮喪的雕塑
Good, 'cause in a few hours you'll be standing here in a frustrated position,
凍在那 而我可以帶著我的朋友們 離開這
frozen, and I'll walk out of here with my buddies and that'll be that.
所以 我不介意等上一整晚
So, I got all night.
真的嗎？一整晚？
Really? All night? Well!
他等不了
He doesn't.
打開籠子
Open that cage.
- 你幹嘛？ - 不許碰我！不許碰我！
- What are you doing? - No touching! No touching!
你敢對我動粗試試
Don't you manhandle me!
- 看吶 小傢伙生氣了 - 傑德？
- Look, he's having a little tantrum. - Jed?
別動 別動 不然你會更難受
Don't you squirm! Don't squirm. It'll only be worse for you.
- 放開他！ - 別害怕
- Put him down! - Don't be afraid.
我不會傷害你的
I shan't hurt you.
我騙你了
I lied.
我想他可等不了一整晚 戴利先生
I don't think he has all night at all, Mr. Daley.
看這速度 他只剩不到一個小時了
From the looks of things, I'd say he has a little over an hour.
放我出去！
Take me out of here!
你是守衛！ 你很瞭解這塊復活金牌
You were the guardian! You know all about this tablet.
而你看上去也比我們這堜狾酗H都聰明
You're obviously much more clever than the rest of us.
不管你知道還是不知道密碼
You may or may not know the combination,
我給你一個小時的時間去想
but I am going to give you exactly one hour to figure it out.
到時間不給我密碼 我就殺光你的朋友
If you do not, I shall kill your friends.
還有你別想溜 我會監視你的行動
And please don't think about escaping, for I shall be watching you.
聽著 我根本無從下手
Look, I don't even know how to begin
我完全不懂怎麼破譯密碼 真的
to decipher this thing, all right? Really.
太可惜了
What a pity.
你的牛仔小朋友看上去那麼惹人喜歡
And your little cowboy friend seemed like such a charming little fellow.
時間在走哦 戴利先生 輪到你行動了
Ah, well. Tick-tock, Mr. Daley. Your hour has begun.
我挺你 夥計 我知道你行的
Hey! You got this, partner. I know you do.
我挺你！
You got this!
你來了！你還好嗎？ 我都快擔心死了！
There you are! Are you all right? I've been worried sick! Sick I tell you.
- 我沒事 - 下一步計劃是什麼 拍檔？
- No, I'm fine. - So what's our next move, partner?
我也不知道 我必須先破譯密碼
I don't know. I just got to get this tablet translated.
哦好極了 又是這傢伙！
Oh, great! This guy again.
聽著夥計 我不想惹麻煩好嗎？
Look, buddy, we don't want any trouble, all right?
看吶
Look at that!
看來冒失的章魚先生僅只是條魚兒
I guess our sassy cephalopod was just a fish
它只是不喜歡離開水
who didn't like being out of water.
看上去也沒那麼討厭嘛
He's not such a ballywagger after all.
好 知道你很高興
Okay. Glad you're happy.
喂 幫個忙好嗎？
Hello? A little assistance?
嘿 泰德 太好了
- Hey, Teddy! Perfect! - Yes!
也許你能幫我們
Maybe you could help us.
我很願意幫忙 但先幫我解決我的燃眉之急
I'd love to help you, but first things first.
鼻子癢的我快瘋掉了
My nose is so itchy, it's driving me insane.
我知道這很無禮 不過我看上去有點缺胳膊少腿
I hate to ask, but, as you see, I'm missing a few body parts.
- 可以幫我撓一下嗎？ - 當然可以
- Could you please give us a scratch? - Yeah, sure.
哦 對是這 再過去一點…
Oh, yes! That's exquisite. A little over there...
- 太棒了！ - 還要？
- Yes! - More?
哦 是的 是的…
Oh, yes! Yes! Oh, that's...
終於舒服了
Sweet rutabaga pie, that was divine.
西奧多·羅斯福很高興為你效勞
Theodore Roosevelt, at your service.
這是美國第二十六屆總統 狂野騎士
Twenty-sixth President of the United States, Rough Rider,
他建造了國家公園 還有很多別的
founder of the national parks, and a whole bunch of other stuff.
- 我們認識嗎？ - 不 還有另一個泰德
- Have we met? - No, there's another Teddy.
紐約的博物館也有一個你
We have one of you in New York.
真的？他長什麼樣？像我一樣？
Really? What's he like, this other me?
差不多 只是…
He's pretty much the same, except with...
只是什麼？只是他多了個身體？
Except what? Say it. Except with a body?
- 是 他有身體 - 哦 見鬼 你刺激到我了
- Yes. He has a body. - Oh, dash it, the pain!
- 還有一匹馬 - 打斷一下
- And a horse. - Excuse me!
我們需要翻譯這塊石板上的文字
We really need someone to translate what's written on this tablet.
- 你看得懂象形文字嗎？ - 是 我懂 小姐
- Do you read hieroglyphics? - Yes, I do, missy.
這很簡單
That's a simple one.
鳥 拿矛的人 斜過來的魚 甲蟲 花瓶
Bird. Man with spear. Sideways fish. Beetle. Vase.
那這代表什麼？
Okay, and what does that mean?
我只是粗略的翻譯一下
It means, and this is just a rough translation,
一個拿矛的男人在一個花瓶
"A man with a spear trapped a bird
抓住了一隻鳥和一條斜過來的魚
and a sideways fish in a vase."
還有一隻甲蟲
"And there was also a beetle."
- 我想你是胡說八道 - 那只是其中一種譯法
- I don't think that's it. - That's just one possible translation.
另一種譯法是
Another possible translation is,
只要能解開法老墓穴深處的秘密
"You will find the combination you seek
你就能破譯密碼
"if you figure out the secret at the heart of Pharaoh's tomb."
好吧 那這又是什麼意思？
Okay, and what does that mean?
不知道！你當我是誰 獅身人面像嗎？
I don't know! What am I, the Sphinx?
「這是什麼」 「那是什麼」
"What's this? What's that?"
你們怎麼不去問紐約那個泰德？
Why don't you ask New York Teddy?
我打賭他會拿他貪婪的雙手摸遍這塊東西
I'm sure he'd love to get his grabby little fingers all over that thing!
可能還會讓他的馬舔兩下！
Probably let his horse lick it, too!
戴利先生 我們應該去雕塑館
Mr. Daley, we should be going to the sculpture gallery.
那兒有個人也許真的能幫助我們
I think there's someone there who might have a better thought on this.
我們要找的人就在這
The fellow we're looking for is just down here.
- 晚上好 - 你好 年輕人
- Bonsoir. - Hello, young lady.
嘿 抱歉 能快點走嗎？
Hey, excuse me. Could we keep moving, please?
當然可以 但我不想錯過這麼好的機會
We certainly could, but then we might miss a rare opportunity.
這可是德加的作品 戴利先生
（德加：法國古典印象主義畫家）
I mean, she is a Degas, Mr. Daley.
我的小朋友被困在沙漏
Okay, it's just I got a little buddy stuck in an hourglass,
明天一早我還有個棘手的會議 對方是沃爾瑪…
I got a pitch meeting at Wal-Mart in the morning...
- 請快點好嗎… - 他就在這兒
- It would be great if we could... - He's right here.
我認為他肯定知道什麼
I think he'll have a thought on this.
思想者先生 抱歉打斷你的沉思
Mr. Thinker, we're sorry to interrupt your contemplation,
可是我們真的想知道法老墓穴深處的秘密
but we really need to figure out the secret at the heart of Pharaoh's tomb.
我在思考 我在思考
I'm thinking. I'm thinking.
我在思考
I'm thinking.
- 我在思考 - 問他沒用
- I'm thinking. - It's not happening with him.
噢 哇哦
Oh, wow.
沒開玩笑吧 看看！
You've gotta be kidding me. Check that out!
嘿 嘿
- Oh, yeah. - Hey! Hey!
夥計 看這兒！這很要緊！
Buddy! Over here! This is serious.
對 生死攸關
Apparently, it's a matter of life and death.
讓我告訴你什麼叫生死攸關
I'll tell you what's a matter of life and death.
看到那個美女嗎
That beautiful lady over there.
嘿寶貝 看看我的肌肉秀
Hey, baby! Check out the gun show going on over here!
猛男！
Firepower!
看來他沒愛因斯坦那種腦子
He's certainly no Einstein.
- 二頭肌！三角肌… - 對了
- Biceps! Deltoids... - Yeah.
- 等等 我見過一堆那個 - 一堆什麼？
- Wait a minute. I saw a bunch of those. - A bunch of whats?
- 小愛因斯坦 - 在哪兒？
- Little Einsteins. - Where?
在航天航空館
Over there, in Air and Space.
得馬上過去
I gotta get over there.
怎麼了？
What?
- 沒什麼 - 那你這麼盯著我幹嘛？
- Nothing. - Okay. Then why are you staring at me?
我不想浪費一秒鐘
I don't wanna miss a moment.
好的 很好 不過我們得快點 因為…
All right, good, but we should get going, 'cause we...
- 幹什麼？ - 你太囉嗦了 牛仔
- Why? - You talk too much, ace.
我也不知道我為什麼吻你 戴利先生
I don't know why I did that, Mr. Daley.
我只覺得我好像沉睡了很久很久
I just feel as if I've been asleep for a long time and now, suddenly,
突然之間 我醒了
I'm awake.
我可以解釋…
I can explain that...
真的 我可以解釋…
But really, I could. I really...
又打我 為什麼？
Again, why?
太好了 你們又回來了
Great, you're back.
好吧 唱得好
Okay. Yeah. Great.
泰坦尼克的主題曲 唱得很好 謝謝你們幫倒忙
Love theme from Titanic. Good, but not really appropriate.
你就不會享受人生嗎 戴利先生？
You don't let yourself enjoy things much, do you, Mr. Daley?
聽著 不是你們選錯歌了 好嗎？
Okay, you know what? It's not really the song choice.
還有 你們真的很煩人
And by the way, you're a little pitchy.
我覺得你們很棒 可愛極了
Well, I thought you were amazing, and you look wonderful.
飛遠點 好嗎？
Could you just fly away, please?
冒險繼續
And so the adventure continues.
叫你們別吵了 聾了嗎？
What did I tell you? Enough!
知道嗎 我感覺自己 像只翩翩起舞的蝴蝶
You know, I do sort of feel like a floating butterfly.
你像只臭蜥蜴
You are crazier than a road lizard.
埃及先生 這兩個人聽說我們要征服世界
Mr. Egypt, these two here heard that we're taking over the world
他們想加入 雖然我不認識他們
and they want in. I don't know who they are,
但他們也是這堛漁i品
but they're on exhibit here, too, apparently.
他們到底是什麼東西
I don't even know what they are.
對不起 我們這兒壞人的名額滿了
I'm sorry, but we're all full up in our axis of evil today. Sorry.
別呀！我很壞 我真的很壞
Come on! But I'm bad! I'm bad!
讓你看看我有多壞
Hey, I could show you how bad I am!
怕我嗎
Fear me!
對不起 我沒被嚇到
I'm sorry. I'm just not buying it.
你看上去不壞 只是脾氣有點差而已
You don't seem very bad. You just seem sort of vaguely grouchy to me.
哦 上帝
Oh, boy.
你在幹嘛？這是什麼？這是什麼？
What are you doing? What is that? What is this?
這是什麼意思？我搞不懂了
What does it mean? You've lost me.
這是你呼吸的聲音嗎？ 吵得我都快不能思考了
Is that you breathing? Because I can't hear myself think.
讓我給你一個建議吧 朋友 別再添亂了
Can I make one suggestion to you, my friend? Just simplify.
這堣w經夠亂的了
There's just too much going on here.
你很邪惡 你有哮喘 你是個機器人
You're evil, you're asthmatic, you're a robot...
還有你這斗篷是幹嘛的？
And what is the cape for?
我們這兒又不是在演話劇
Are we going to the opera? I don't think so.
不好意思！再見
Sorry! Goodbye.
有情況！
Attention!
他帶著金牌逃了
He's leaving with the tablet!
哪堙H
Where?
讓我看
Give me that.
他不是在想密碼 他要逃跑！
He's not trying to figure out the... He's trying to escape!
所有人給我追 殺了他！ 把金牌帶回來給我
Go. Go! All of you! Kill him! And bring me that tablet.
行動起來 快 金牌是我們一切的希望
Come on, people! Let's go! Without that tablet, we've nothing!
士兵們 上！
Streltsy! Go!
你逃不出我的手掌 拉瑞·戴利
Thought you could get away, didn't you, Larry Daley?
老天 我們玩完了
Criminy, we're jimmy-jacked.
- 玩完了？是嗎？ - 我就是這麼說話的
- Jimmy-jacked? Really? - It's the way I speak.
我明白你的意思 就是聽上去有點奇怪
Yeah, I know, but that one sounds made up, even for you.
「不 不 我們的路被壞人堵住了」
"Oh, no, our path has been blocked by bad people."
這麼說還有什麼意思？
What's the fun in that?
問題是我們現在去不了航天航空館了
The point is, we're not getting into the Air and Space right now.
- 你說的對 我們玩完了 - 玩完了
- You're right. We are jimmy-jacked. - Jimmy-jacked.
快
Come on.
他們都說那個總統是個好人
They say a good man rules this union.
我答應過傑迪戴亞我會找人幫忙
I promised Jedediah I would bring help,
我一定會找到
and help I will bring.
進攻！
Charge!
低估這段距離了
Misjudged the distance.
誰？
Who's there?
朱庇特神 求你護佑我
Jupiter, protect me.
一動不動
Remain very still.
他們對移動很敏感
They can sense movement.
顯然 他們也能聽到我自言自語
Apparently, they can also hear me talking to myself.
我不是堅果
I'm not a nut.
不要！
No!
在這婺一會兒吧
We should be okay in here for a while.
你當守衛多久了？
So, how long have you guarded antiquities?
什麼？哦 其實我不在這兒工作…
What? Oh, no, I don't actually work at the...
你的裝備看上去很齊全 所以我以為…
I just thought with the fancy getup and all...
這是我借的
No, I borrowed this.
我在紐約確實當過守衛 那是很久以前了
I mean, I was a guard back in New York, but that was a while ago.
為什麼不幹了？不喜歡了嗎？
So why did you leave? Did you not enjoy it?
不 我愛這份工作 只是…
No, I loved it. I just...
人生往另一個方向在發展 所以…
Things sort of took off in a different direction, so...
- 那你現在的工作是什麼？ - 怎麼說呢…
- So what do you do now? - Well, I sort of...
我發明產品然後銷售出去
Well, I sort of design products and sell them.
- 你是發明家！ - 是的
- You're an inventor! - I am.
我是個發明家 發明東西
I am an inventor, yeah. I invent stuff.
比如火箭？
Like the rocket ship?
- 不是 - 水上飛機？
- No. - The sea plane.
- 飛船？ - 不 不是飛行器
- The dirigible? - No, not aircraft.
小一點的東西 比如…
Sort of like more small-scale stuff, like...
比如夜光手電筒 那是我的發明
Well, the Glow-in-the-Dark Flashlight, that was mine.
那麼你喜歡這份新工作嗎？
So this new job, do you like it?
是 我很喜歡 很刺激…
Yeah, I like it a lot. It's exciting. It's...
- 怎麼了？ - 我只是有點奇怪
- What? - I'm just confused, is all.
既然你一點都不興奮 那你為什麼幹那個？
If you're not excited by it, why do you do it?
- 我很興奮 我只是… - 別瞞我了 戴利先生
- I am excited by it. I just said... - I know what you said, Mr. Daley,
我眼前這個人很明顯已經喪失了激情
but what I see in front of me is a man who's lost his moxie.
我沒有…
I have not lost my...
我很有激情
I got my moxie.
知道我為什麼當飛行員嗎？
Do you know why I became a pilot?
- 不知道 - 因為那充滿樂趣
- I don't, no. - For the fun of it.
沒有樂趣人生還有什麼意義？
Why else would anyone do anything?
了不起的蓋茨比！
Great Gatsby!
走開 你們這些叫個不停的鴿子
Blast these pigeons and their incessant cooing!
- 別！總統先生！ - 好了 是時候看看…
- No! Mr. President! Sir! - All right. Time to see the state...
- 請別起來！ …我們偉大的聯邦了！我總是說
- Please don't get up! ...of this great union! I always say,
今天能幹完的事就別留到明天
leave nothing for tomorrow which can be done today.
先生 你出去會嚇倒一片人的
Sir, if you go out there, you're gonna freak a lot of people out!
嚇人？胡說八道 我不是怪物
Freak? I assure you, sir, I am no freak.
- 我不是說你是怪物… - 行了 小東西
- No, I didn't mean you're a freak... - Come here, little one.
真要說嚇人的話 你才嚇死人了
In fact, if anyone is freakish, I'm afraid it's you, sir.
你也實在是太小了
The truth is, you are very small.
和正常人比你也算矮小的
And I mean even for a regular-sized human.
什麼？為什麼這麼說？
What? Why would you even say that?
我是實話實說
I must be honest.
好吧 你很誠實 你說的對
Right. Okay, Honest Abe. Of course. I'm sorry. Great.
好了 總統先生 把小傢伙放下來
Come, now, Mr. President, put the little man down
把你的屁股放回你的寶座上
and let's sit our fanny back in that throne of yours.
既然你那麼堅定 那我就照辦吧
You have a can-do attitude, and I shall do as you ask.
謝謝
Thank you.
- 站好了 - 謝謝
- There you go. - Thank you.
堅定不移正是我們民族的偉大精神
It's that very can-do spirit that has defined this remarkable nation of ours.
- 我講個故事 - 他們追來了
- Interesting story. - They're coming.
有一天晚上在蓋茲堡…
One night in Gettysburg...
總統先生 請你先別動
Mr. President, we're gonna need you to hold still now.
- 什麼？ - 亞伯拉罕 不許動！
- What? - Abraham, freeze!
不許動？我…
Freeze? I...
- 謝謝 - 不客氣
- Thank you. - You're welcome.
- 快 我們去航天航空館 - 允許我說一句
- Come on, let's get to Air and Space. - Lf I may,
- 你們倆真是太相配了 - 不 我們不配…
- you two make an adorable couple. - Oh, no, we're not...
不 你搞錯了…我們不是…
No, we're not a... I mean, we're not a...
什麼不配不配 少來了
"We're not a... I mean, we're not a..."
我從不撒謊
I never lie!
事實就是 你們倆個在一起太相配了
The truth is, you two are adorable together.
謝謝 晚安
Thank you. Good night.
再見 美麗的女士還有小個子男人
Farewell, lovely lady and small, little man.
看看能不能找到你說的愛因斯坦們
Now let's see if we can find these Einsteins of yours.
我的一小步 是人類的一大步
One giant leap for a mannequin...
華盛頓 這堿O航天航空館 全體啟動 全速運行
D.C., this is Air and Space. We are back online and fully operational.
黑色轟炸機又一次開始行軍
The Tuskegee Airmen are on the march once again.
不用直播我們的每一個行動吧 享受當前的時刻吧
Can you stop narrating everything we're doing? Just live in the moment.
黑色轟炸機正在享受當前的時刻
The Tuskegee Airmen are living in the moment!
- 埃爾哈特小姐 - 你好
- Miss Earhart? - Yes.
- 我想對你表示感謝 - 謝我什麼 上尉？
- I wanna say thank you. - What for, Captain?
很多人都認為我們成不了飛行員
A lot of people didn't think we could fly, either.
謝謝你讓大家改變了想法
Thanks for clearing the runway, ma'am.
- 比比誰先到巴黎？ - 接受挑戰！
- Race you to Paris? - You're on!
不 現在不行 我們…
No! Not now! We gotta...
- 打個來回很快的 - 不行 我們是來找愛因斯坦的
- It's just a quick jaunt over the pond. - No. Gotta find the Einsteins.
快點 我們沒時間了 快
Come on, we gotta go. We don't have time. Come on!
抱歉 看到飛機我就忍不住了
Sorry, it's in the blood.
看那兒 戴利先生
There she is, Mr. Daley.
老貝茜 我的老搭檔了 她帶著我飛越了大西洋
Old Bessie, the old family bus. That gal took me across the Atlantic!
好吧 不過愛因斯坦在那邊
Okay. I think the Einsteins are over here, though.
這堿O指揮中心 起飛檢查完畢
This is Mission Control. Flight check complete.
- 他們去哪兒了？ - 發射準備完畢
- Where'd you go? Where'd they go? - You are clear for launch.
起飛！
Contact!
華盛頓 這堿O控制中心
D.C., this is Mission Control.
- 不 不 不！ - 所有系統檢查完畢 準備發射
- No, no! No! - All systems go and green for lift-off.
收到 準備發射
Roger that. We are green for lift-off.
不 絕對不能發射！
No, we're definitely not green for any kind of lift-off!
- 到底發射不發射 - 我說不發射
- I want a "go, no-go" for launch. - I say no-go. Let's not go.
發射！
Go!
- 發射！ - 不！不能發射！
- Go! - No! No go!
啟動最大扭矩
Torquing angles incoming.
別放大扭矩 降低扭矩
Tone it down with the torque. Torque it down.
降低扭矩 降低扭矩
De-torque. De-torque.
開始點火倒計時
Commence ignition sequence.
- 收到 - 收到發射指令
- Roger that, flight. - We have launch commit.
- 不 不 不 不！ - 十
- No. No, no, no! - Ten,
九 八 七…
nine, eight, seven...
- 嘿 那是我的 - 不 沒有發射指令
- Hey, that's mine. - No, we do not have commit.
重複 沒有發射指令
Repeat. We are decommissioning the committal of the launch
發射指令無效 禁止發射 禁止起飛
and it is now a negatory launch phase. We are in a no-fly, no-go phase.
嚴禁任何起飛行為！
That is a November-Gorgon phase of non-flying!
- 好吧！ - 祝各位晚安
- Fine! - And we're gonna say good night.
謝謝大家 幹得好 完畢 解散
Thank you. Good work. Over and out.
- 對不起 - 見鬼 真掃興
- Sorry. - Damn, that was disappointing.
來吧 我請你喝咖啡
Come on. I'll buy you a cup of coffee.
你好 太空猴
Hey, little space monkey.
你叫亞伯 很好 你好嗎？
You're Able. Okay, good. How you doing?
哦 很好 稍息 好的
Yes, good. At ease. All right.
你非常有禮貌
You're a polite little fella, aren't you?
你知道那些愛因斯坦搖頭娃娃在哪兒嗎？
Hey, you happen to know where those little Einstein bobblehead guys are?
戴利先生！我找到愛因斯坦了
Mr. Daley! I found your Einsteins.
太好了…
Great. Hey...
先生們 我們需要你們幫我們 破譯這塊金牌的密碼
Gentlemen, we're trying to crack the combination of this tablet doodad,
金牌上的文字告訴我們
and the writing here says we'll find it
要破譯密碼必須破譯法老墓穴深處的秘密
if we figure out the secret at the heart of Pharaoh's tomb.
很簡單 答案就蘊含在問題中
That's an easy one. The answer's in the question.
- 什麼意思？ - 破譯
- What does that mean? - "Figure out".
就是計算 比如 一個數字
It's a figure! I.e., a number.
法老的墓穴 就是金字塔
And the Pharaoh's tomb, i.e. The pyramids.
還不明白嗎 孩子？ 你們要找的就是藏在金字塔中的
Don't you get it, kid? You're looking for the secret number
那串神秘數字
at the heart of the pyramids.
哦 我懂了 答案就是圓周率！
Well, whistle me Dixie, the answer's pi!
- 圓周率？ - 3.14159265 精確的來說
- Pi? - 3.14159265, to be exact.
對！3.1495265
Yes! 3.1495265.
不是 是3.14159265
No, no, no, 3.14159265.
好吧 3.14…
Yeah, okay, 3.14...
對不起 我實在分不清 你們是在點頭還是搖頭…
I'm sorry, I can't tell. Is it yes or no? Cause you just...
我知道這對你們很難 能不能…
I know it's hard, could you just...
別碰頭髮
Don't touch the hair.
對不起 你們的頭晃得我頭暈…
Sorry, I can't tell if it's up or...
我是個搖頭娃娃 笨蛋
I'm a bobblehead, dummkopf,
我們就愛搖頭晃腦 一起說
and that's the way we like it. All together, now!
我們就愛搖頭晃腦
That's the way We like it
知道嗎 不是人人都能當愛因斯坦…
You know, we can't all be Einsteins, so...
- 我能！ - 我們是
- I can! - We are!
- 他是 - 我也是
- He is! - Me, too!
- 好吧 - 好 我再說一遍
- Okay, all right. - Okay, here it is.
- 可不可以說慢一點 - 好的
- Can you slow it down a little bit? - Okay.
3.14159265.
- 好的 3.14… - 我記住了
- Okay. 3.14... - I've got it.
- 謝謝 愛因斯坦先生 - 謝謝
- Thank you, Mr. Einsteins. - Thank you.
好了 作為一名偉大的將軍
All right. Now, like the brilliant and famous general that I am,
經過一番深思熟慮
I thought long and hard about what you said,
我又想出了全新的升級版作戰計劃
and I've come up with a brand-new and improved battle plan!
聽著
Okay.
我會大聲宣佈
I will loudly announce that we are not
全體不攻擊 然後…
going to attack, and then...
等待時機
Wait for it.
然後大家隨便閒扯 突然
"What's the amazing Custer about to say now? I hope he's my friend, or..."
發動攻擊！
We attack!
沒想到你的朋友自己逃命去了吧？
Didn't expect your friend to run off like that, did you?
他會回來的 妖怪
He's coming back, Ka-Ka-Ro.
他很快就會回來救我
Sure as moon shines on a mongoose, he'll be here.
如果我是你就省點力氣
I would save my breath if I were you.
你離被悶死已經不遠了
You don't have many left.
還有十分鐘傑德就要被淹沒了
We've got about 10 minutes to get over there to Jed.
我覺得我們的合作很愉快 也許我們的關係能更進一步
I think we make a good team, perhaps more than a team.
等等 等一下
Wait. Okay, wait.
怎麼了？你不喜歡吻我嗎？
What's the matter? You didn't like kissing me?
不 我喜歡 感覺棒極了 我是說
No, I did. It was great. I mean,
被扇耳光有那麼點疼 不過…
the slapping hurt a little bit, but...
- 就是說你不喜歡我 - 我當然喜歡你 你非常特別
- So you don't like me, then. - Of course I like you. You're incredible.
你讓人無法抗拒…
I think you're an amazing person. You're...
但我們之間存在著一些障礙…
It's just there are certain issues that would prevent us from...
- 我只是…你不是… - 我不是什麼戴利先生？
- I just... You're not... - I'm not what, Mr. Daley?
好吧 你的身體是…
Okay. You're made of...
身體是…
Made of...
美好的東西 你的身體非常美好 非常了不起
Wonderful things. You're made of good, wonderful things.
走吧
Come on.
男士們 能幫我們擋一會兒嗎？
Gentlemen, could you buy us some time please?
看來只有這個辦法了
It'll have to do.
不要！那是人類發明的第一架飛機
No! That's the first plane ever made!
它是用木板做的紙糊的
It's made out of balsa wood and paper.
它是用雲杉木和帆布做的
It's made out of spruce and canvas
匯聚了老一代美國人的精巧工藝
and good old-fashioned American ingenuity.
你到底上不上來？
Are you coming, or what?
- 讓開！ - 沒門
- Out of our way! - I don't think so.
他們逃了！
They're getting away!
抓穩了戴利先生 這事兒越來越有意思了
Hang on, Mr. Daley. Things are about to get interesting.
是個女的在開！她是不是瘋了
A lady pilot! Preposterous!
- 看清楚 小子們 - 哦 她飛得真好
- Think again, boys! - Oh, she's good.
怎麼了 怎麼了？
What? What?
一根線卡住了 我去鬆開它
One of the wires is jammed. I'm going to have to loosen it.
- 你來控制方向桿 - 不 我不要！
- Here, take the stick! - No! I'm not gonna... No!
我知道你還有激情
I know you've got moxie in you yet.
有激情不代表會開飛機 開飛機要飛行執照的
Moxie doesn't fly planes! People who have pilots' licenses fly planes!
- 好吧 - 交給你了
- Okay. - She's all yours.
不要吧！我不要這個
I don't want it! I don't want the stick!
別到處看戴利先生 你在駕駛飛機
Don't look now, Mr. Daley, but you're flying an airplane!
亞伯！開門！
Able! The doors!
- 行了！ - 下降！
- Got it! - Pull!
拉升！
Pull up!
好樣的！
Yes!
一路順風 阿梅莉亞·埃爾哈特
Godspeed, Amelia Earhart!
一路順風
Godspeed.
你有點緊張啊 蠢豬
Look a little nervous there, Ramen Noodle.
我就當是做熱沙按摩
'Cause for me, this is like a spa treatment.
沙浴能幫助我恢復活力 去角質的
Sand baths are really rejuvenating for the skin. Exfoliates.
你放棄了吧
Giving up yet?
還沒有
Not quite yet, no.
我可以讓時間流逝的更快些
In fact, let's see if we can't make time fly.
什麼怪聲音？
What is that funny sound?
站住！
Stop!
站住別動 戴利先生
Right there, please, Mr. Daley.
哇 哇…
Well. Well, well, well!
你的出場很漂亮啊 戴利先生
You certainly know how to make an entrance, Mr. Daley.
該去挖點援軍來了
Time to recruit some backup.
你朋友快淹死了
I hope for your little friend's sake, here,
但願你已經想到了密碼
that you also figured out the combination.
- 把傑德給我 - 哦 不不不
- Give me Jed. - Oh, no, no, no.
先給我密碼 還有金牌
First, give me the combination and hand over that tablet.
我會把金牌和密碼給你
I'll give you the tablet and the combination
不過你先放了我的朋友們 還有把他給我
when you release my friends and give him back to me.
我願意什麼時候放人就什麼時候放人
I shall release what I want to release the moment I want to release it.
好極了 那我什麼時候願意給你
Great. And I'll release what I want to release
我就什麼時候給你 怎麼樣？
at the exact moment that I want to release it, okay?
給我密碼和金牌 馬上
Tell me the combination and give me that tablet right now
否則我就殺光你的朋友
or I shall kill all of your friends,
首先拿這個鬍子拉楂的小牛仔開刀
starting with the little shaggy-headed little cowman here.
我才不鬍子拉楂 鐵人 把這個壞蛋交給我
I ain't shaggy-headed! Gigantor, let me take this guy!
別擔心 我能處理 你不先放了我的朋友
Don't worry, I got this handled. You don't want to give me my friends,
你就別想拿到密碼和金牌
then you're not gonna get your combination or your tablet.
- 好吧 你給我聽好 - 好的
- All right, I'll tell you what. - Good.
我的外號不是什麼值得信賴的卡門拉
They didn't call me Kahmunrah the Trustworthy for nothing.
給你 我的外號不叫值得信賴的卡門拉
Here you go. They didn't call me Kahmunrah the Trustworthy!
他們叫我嗜血卡門拉
They called me Kahmunrah the Bloodthirsty,
這個卡門拉想要什麼
who kills whoever doesn't give Kahmunrah exactly what he wants
就要立刻得到
in the moment that he wants it, which is right now,
這個卡門拉現在要的就是金牌和密碼
when I had also better get the combination and the tablet!
- 你的外號很長啊 - 用埃及語會短一些
- That's what they called you? - It was shorter in Egyptian.
很好 把他給我 我就給你密碼和金牌
Great, I'll give you the combination after you give him back.
我看你再敢碰它一下 我就立刻殺了你
How dare you? If you touch that again, I shall kill you right now.
- 好吧 - 別碰它
- Okay. - Do not touch this.
- 這堿O禁止觸碰區域！ - 好 好吧…
- This is a no-touching zone! - Good. Well, then...
哦上帝 我簡直不敢相信你又過界了
Oh, my God! I can't believe you reached across like that again!
難以置信 上帝 我真想馬上殺了你…
I can't even believe it! Oh, God, I want to kill you right...
要不是你知道密碼 你早就沒命了
If you didn't know this combination, you'd be so dead right now,
- 你會死的很難看 - 可惜我知道密碼
- it would be unbelievable. - Great, but I do know the combination.
不許你的手越過這條線
Don't cross this line with your hand!
膽大包天！如果你再囉嗦一句 我就殺了你
How dare you! If you speak again, I'm going to kill you.
聽明白沒有？
Do you understand this?
不許說話 上帝 我看到你嘴巴動了
Don't say it! Oh, God, I see you getting ready.
- 我沒想開口說話 - 哦 上帝 不許說話
- I wasn't gonna say anything. - Oh, my God, don't say anything.
你再說一句我就掐死你
I shall murder you if you talk again.
把金牌和密碼給我
Now give me that tablet and tell me the combination.
可以 你先放了傑德還有我的朋友
Okay. After you give me Jed and release my friends.
- 你又犯規了 - 什麼？
- You did all three! - What?
你不僅說話了而且又把手伸過來了
You spoke and you reached your hand across!
聽著 我可以跟你繞一晚上
Look. I can talk to you about this all night, okay?
- 不如這樣 - 你給我聽好…
- How about this? - Look, just give...
我可以先不殺你 雖然我很想很想殺了你
How about I don't kill you right now, like I really, really want to,
我給你五秒鐘的時間
and I give you precisely five seconds
交出金牌和密碼
to give me that tablet and tell me the combination?
我們知道密碼了 是圓周率
We already got the combination. It's pi.
- 3.14159265 - 不！
- 3.14159265. - No!
- 嘿 - 對不起
- Hey. - Sorry.
這個怪老頭 還會唱歌 唱起來像只金絲雀
So Crazy Hair here, he sang. Oh, did he sing! Like a canary.
對不起 拉瑞
I'm sorry, Larry.
你少廢話！忘了教訓了？
Enough out of you! Remember what happened last time?
- 住手 - 蠢貨
- That's enough. - Stupid man.
- 你沒事吧？ - 沒事 謝謝
- You okay? - Yeah, thanks.
你肯定氣壞了吧 拉瑞
Must be a real bummer for you, Larry,
你失去了所有的籌碼
knowing that all of your valiant efforts were, in the end, for naught.
你肯定沮喪到不行
What a terrible disappointment you must be to yourself.
聽到嗡嗡聲了沒有？
Do you hear that humming sound?
知道這是什麼聲音嗎？
Do you know what that sound is?
我在用修辭
It's rhetorical.
那就是末日的聲音
That is the sound of the End.
對不起 傑德
I'm sorry, Jed.
你盡力了鐵人
You did your best, Gigantor.
見鬼 我們差點就贏了
Dadgum it, we almost had him, too.
不 我是說我很抱歉 前幾年我一直不在博物館
No, I mean, I'm sorry I wasn't around the last couple of years at the museum.
- 否則這一切都不會發生 - 你還不明白嗎 鐵人？
- Maybe none of this would have happened. - You don't get it, do you, Gigantor?
我打給你不是我們需要幫助
I didn't call you 'cause we needed your help.
我們確實有點小麻煩
Sure, we were in a little pickle,
但這不是我第一次
but it wouldn't have been the first time
被沙緊緊地埋在下面
I had to wrestle my way out of a root sack.
不是 夥計 我打給你是因為你需要我們
No, partner. I called you 'cause you needed us.
這幾年來你一直把自己隱藏在 那套光鮮的西服
That fancy suit you've been parading around in these past couple years,
但在我看來 那只是一個軀殼
that there's a hanging suit.
如同行屍走肉
All gussied up, but dead inside.
那不是你
That ain't you.
- 還有件事 - 什麼
- And I'll tell you another thing. - Yeah.
今夜還沒結束
This night ain't over yet.
我這個小小的午夜牛仔 還有無窮的戰鬥力
This little Midnight Cowboy's got some fight left in him.
你也有 不要氣餒
Something tells me you do, too. Ho, now!
卡門拉的統治時代到來了
Welcome to the new, extended reign of Kahmunrah,
埃及第五代君王
Fifth King of Egypt
現在將統治世界！
and now the world!
我的軍隊 前進！
Horus, Ra, my warriors, come forth!
把拉瑞·戴利和他的朋友送進地獄！
Send Larry Daley and his friends to their doom!
住手！
Halt!
偉大的奧克塔維厄斯回來了！
The mighty Octavius has returned!
我騎著全世界最最令人聞風喪膽的動物 我騎著
I ride on the back of nature's most fearsome creature! I ride
一隻松鼠！
the squirrel!
前進 我的戰馬！
Forward now, my mighty steed!
悠著點 姑娘
Whoa, girl! Easy.
你選擇繳械投降
Do you wish to surrender honorably?
還是血濺沙場？
Or must this end with the spilling of your blood?
就這個？這就是你的援軍？
This? This is your big rescue?
不 這才是！
Oh, no. This is!
這是什麼東西？
What is that thing?
我是亞伯拉罕·林肯
The name is Abraham Lincoln.
- 先生 你的麻煩大了 - 殺了他！
- And you, sir, are in a heap of trouble! - Attack it!
噁心的半鳥人
Disgusting half-pigeons!
不 不 不！等等！
No, no, no! Hello?
滾吧 鳥人
Adios, bird brains!
等等 等等 別！
Wait, wait, wait. No, no!
再見了 鳥人
Goodbye, strange birdmen.
別回地下世界！
Do not return to the Underworld!
對 對 回你們老家去吧！
Yes, yes, do go back into the Underworld!
謝謝光臨 晚安！
Thank you for coming! Good night!
不 不！
No, no!
真是尷尬
Oh, this is awkward.
這兒好像沒我什麼事了
It appears my work here is done.
記住我的話孩子 家庭不睦 萬事不興
Just remember, son, a house divided against itself cannot stand.
再見
Farewell.
- 現在怎麼辦？ - 我也不知道怎麼辦
- What now? - You know, I'm not quite sure.
我要看到他死
I suppose we should probably start by watching him die.
士兵 殺了他
Streltsy! Make him dead!
又怎麼了？
Now what?
我們現在不準備
We are not going to attack right
攻擊！
now!
給我上！
Get them!
別擔心 拉瑞 我去救傑迪戴亞！
Fear not, Larry! I will help Jedediah!
你去後面包抄
You come at them from behind!
- 嘿 你在幹嘛？ - 我在找地方隱蔽
- Hey, what's going on? - I'm hiding.
隱蔽？你在搞什麼！ 快 我們這兒需要你
Hiding? What are you doing? Come on, we need you.
- 我是個失敗者 - 不 你不是
- I'm a failure. - No, you're not.
你試過愚蠢地帶領208個美國人打仗 最後全軍覆滅
Did you foolishly lead 208 Americans to their deaths
就在小比格霍恩河戰役？
at the Battle of Little Bighorn?
- 沒有 - 沒有 那感覺不好 真的不好
- No. - No? Not good. Not good at all.
- 感覺不好 - 當然 我也就能動動嘴皮子
- That's not good. - Sure, I talk a good game,
干真的不行 我不配肩膀上的軍銜
but the truth of the matter is, I don't deserve these stars.
人們永遠只記得我的失敗
I will always be famous for my biggest failure.
嘿
Hey.
過去的就讓它過去 好嗎？
The past is the past, okay?
現在 當下 就在今夜
Right now, this moment, this night,
這場戰役將永垂青史
this is what you're gonna be remembered for.
這是你的最後一戰
This is your last stand.
- 我們需要一位領袖 - 是啊 他們需要領袖
- They need a leader. - Yeah, they need a leader.
是嗎？你願意去領導他們嗎？
Yeah? You want to be their leader, huh?
- 是 我願意 - 那就站起來！
- Yeah, I do. - Let's do this!
- 怎麼樣？ - 好
- All right? - Yeah.
我們走！
Let's go!
太糟了！
Not good!
拉瑞！
Larry!
嘿 亞伯！
Hey, Able!
我需要幫助
I want to help!
哦 好的
Oh, great.
你是誰？這是我的博物館
Who are you? This is my museum!
他是我的人 你走開
Well, he's my human. Back off!
你儘管拉人 你這個野蠻人
You need all the help you can get, Jungle-Dweller!
少廢話 你這個太空佬
Get over yourself space snob!
夥計們！嘿 夥計們！
Guys! Hey, guys!
現在不是爭這些的時候 好嗎？
This is not the time to get into this, all right?
德克斯特 你知道規矩
Dexter, you know better.
好嗎 再胡鬧就請你們吃耳光
All right? That's what happens when you do that!
給你一耳光
You get that.
住手 都給我住手！
Stop! Just stop! Stop!
聽著 你們都是高貴的僧帽猴
Now, listen. You're both proud capuchin!
應該一直對外 抗擊外敵
You need to concentrate on slapping the enemy!
團結起來 行嗎？
Keep it together, all right?
快 衝上去 給我打
Come on, let's go! Let's do it!
- 傑迪戴亞 大家需要我們 - 我恐怕不行了
- Jedediah! They need us! - I ain't gonna make it!
恐怕我的日子到頭了
Afraid this cowboy's been to his last hoedown.
奧克塔維厄斯 記住我的精神 自由 狂野…
Octavius, remember me as I was, wild, and free, and...
- 還不是說遺言的時候 - 我還沒說完
- No need for final words. - I'm not finished yet.
我還想回憶一下我們的那段事
I want to get to the story of our relationship,
我們是怎麼從敵人變成朋友的
the evolution from enemy to friends.
- 不要！ - 你想哭就哭吧！
- No! - It'll make you cry!
不！因為你還死不了！
No! Because you are going to live!
- 該我們上場了 - 拿著劍
- Let's go to work. - Have a sword.
拿劍來！
Sword!
上面！
Incoming!
好疼
That smarts.
你打 你踢！ 你打 你踢！
You smack, you kick! You smack, you kick!
你打 你踢！ 幹得漂亮 夥計們！
You smack, you kick! Teamwork, fellas! Wunderbar!
你們好啊 夥計們！
How you doing, fellas?
- 你還好嗎？ - 再好沒有
- Are you all right? - Never better.
聽著 一看到我的信號就立刻打開門
Listen, when I give you the signal, I want you to open the gate.
- 看來你成竹在胸 - 我要去搞點小破壞
- I take it you have a plan. - I'm gonna divide the house.
金牌給我 馬上！
The tablet! Now!
好的 當然 我會給你
Okay, sure, you can have it.
告訴我你們誰是頭 我就給他
Just tell me who the boss is and I'll give it to you.
要不我給卡門拉? 他看上去是你們頭 不是嗎？
Or should I give it to Kahmunrah? He's your master, right?
放屁 他才不是什麼頭
Nyet! He is not our master!
是嗎？我看一直是他在說了算
Really? 'Cause he acts like he is.
算了 你就告訴我你們誰是頭 我就給誰
But fine, just tell me who the boss is and you can have it.
我是頭！
Hey! That'd be me.
他是個農民 我才是這堸艉@有貴族血統的人
This man is a peasant! I am the only one here of noble birth!
是嗎？可是他看上去有更多勳章 帽子也更大 不過…
Really? 'Cause he's got more medals and a bigger hat, but...
- 謝謝 - 你確實有很多勳章
- Thank you. - You might got a lot of medals,
但是你要再敢用你的小手碰一下金牌
but you put one of your little child hands on that tablet again,
我就要你好看
it'll be the last thing them tiny little mitts of yours ever touch.
你幹嘛要傷害小拿拿？
Why would you touch little Nippy?
我能自己解決 好嗎？
I can handle this, okay?
你什麼也解決不了 你連話都說不清楚 蠢貨！
You can handle nothing! You can barely speak, you fool!
沒問題 你要是嗎 我給你
You know what? No problem. I'll give it to you. You see that?
你這個小雜種
Oh, you're a spunky little fella!
幹得漂亮 戴利先生 讓他們自相殘殺
Very clever, Mr. Daley, getting them to fight amongst themselves.
對 我不敢邀功 這主意是亞伯拉罕·林肯想出來的
Yeah. I can't really take credit. It was Abraham Lincoln's idea.
家庭不睦 萬事不興…
You know, a house divided can't...
- 還做得不夠 - 沒錯
- Doesn't do well. - Yes, well,
剛才你就應該自己逃命的
you should have saved yourself when you had the chance,
可惜你又落在了我手
because now I shall have the tremendous pleasure
我現在最想做的事就是親手殺了你
of killing you myself!
你到底是什麼人？
What are you?
我是個守衛
I'm the night guard.
不！
No!
勝利屬於我們！
Victory is ours!
耶！
Yeah!
我說什麼來著！
That's what I'm talking about!
耶！
Yeah!
我看到有個人終於找回他的激情了
I'd say somebody found his moxie.
史密森尼戰役
The Battle of the Smithsonian.
將是一場永遠不為人知的偉大戰役
Perhaps the greatest battle the world will never know.
我們都見證了
We'll know.
是啊
Yeah.
噢 老天 還有一個小時就天亮了 我得把你們都弄回去
Oh, man, I got an hour till sunrise. I got to get you guys back.
我不得不提醒你鐵人 那兒的人不再需要我們了
In case you forgot, Gigantor, they don't want us there anymore.
不 我需要
Well, I do.
嘿 可以載我們一程嗎？
Hey, think you could hook us up with a ride?
當然 我很榮幸
My pleasure, of course.
稍等 我還有件事要辦
Hang on a second. One last thing I got to take care of.
快 孩子！來啊
Come on, boy! Come on, come on!
跳進去！
Get in there!
很舒服吧？
Feels good, right?
別客氣！ 記得天亮前一定要回去！
You're welcome! Just get back inside by sunrise, okay?
這真是一個光明的時代
These are promising days, indeed.
好了 夥計們 動作快
All right. Hey, come on, guys.
記得和同伴呆在一起
Remember, stay with your buddy, all right?
好 好
Good, good.
好了 你回到該回的地方了
Well, you're back where you belong.
我想是的
Yeah. Think so.
我想我該走了
I guess I should be going.
阿梅莉亞
Hey, Amelia.
早些時候我想告訴你的那件事…
That thing that I was trying to tell you about earlier...
我真的很難說出口
There's not really an easy way to put this,
- 但是 一旦天亮… - 我知道會發生什麼 戴利先生
- but, in the morning... - I know what's coming, Mr. Daley.
我一直知道
I've always known.
不過沒關係
But it doesn't matter.
在一夜之間 你給了我一生都未曾體驗過的冒險經歷
You've given me the adventure of a lifetime in one night.
我覺得今天的日出一定特別美麗
And I have a feeling it's going to be a beautiful sunrise.
要快樂
Have fun.
謝謝
Thanks.
不知道你怎麼想 夥計 可這個老牛仔才攻到二壘
I don't know about you fellas, but this old cowboy just got to second base.
- 她飛走了 - 頭也不回…
- There she goes. - Straight towards...
加拿大
Canada.
她在往加拿大飛
She's heading to Canada.
航向正確
No, now she course-corrected.
去地下室 夥計們
Here, head on downstairs, guys.
- 好的 - 晚上好 拉瑞
- All righty. - Good night, Larry.
孩子 你好嗎？
Hey, boy, how's it going?
勞倫斯！謝謝你把他們都帶回來
Lawrence! Bless you for bringing them back.
你幹的真是太漂亮了
And might I say, a hearty well-done is in order.
可是他們不能在地下室躲一輩子
And may I also point out, they cannot hide in the basement forever.
不 我已經想到辦法了
Yeah. No, I think I got that figured out.
- 真的 - 對
- Really? - Yeah.
日出 笨瓜
Sun come, dum-dum.
我們摩艾朋友說的對 日出即將來臨
Our moai friend is right. The dawn will soon be upon us.
泰德
Hey, Teddy.
還記得那天晚上你和我說的嗎
Remember the other night you were saying something
你說幸福的關鍵是
about the key to happiness?
- 我說了嗎？ - 你說：「幸福的關鍵是…」
- Did I? - You said, "The key to happiness is..."
然後太陽出來你就凍住了
And then the sun came up and you froze.
- 我想我知道答案了 - 是嗎？
- I think I got it figured out. - Yes?
就是做你愛做的事 對不對 和你愛的人在一起
It's doing what you love, isn't it? With people you love.
其實 我想說的是「鍛煉身體」
Actually, I was going to say "physical exercise",
不過你說的也不錯
but the love thing's good, too.
- 勞倫斯 - 什麼
- Lawrence! - Yeah.
歡迎回家 孩子
Welcome home, son.
謝謝
Thanks.
朋友們 漫長的等待終於結束 經過了2個月的整修
Well, folks, the wait is over. After two months of renovation,
今夜 自然歷史博物館將重新對公眾開放
tonight, The Museum of Natural History reopens its doors to the public.
如你所見 紐約市民正迫不及待的涌進博物館
As you can see, New Yorkers are flooding in,
想親身體驗博物館
eager to see just what changes are in store.
新推出的夜遊項目
With its new, extended night hours,
據說夜間博物館的展品 比以往更加栩栩如生
we're told the museum will be more lively than ever.
都過了這麼久了 這身制服倒還合身
I see the uniform still fits after these long, long years.
是啊 不過也沒過多久嘛…
Yeah, yeah. Really hasn't been that long, but...
那麼 這場喜慶回歸的代價是什麼？
So, to what do we owe this "triumphant" return?
還是適應不了商場 被裁了？
Not cut out for the "corporate" jungle after all. Got fired.
實際上 我把公司賣了
No, actually, I sold my company.
這個世界的變化令人難以捉摸
The world doth move in mysterious ways.
前一天我們還在清理所有老展品
One day, we've got to get rid of everything old,
後一天 一個富有的無名氏突然捐助了博物館一大筆資金
the next, a rich, anonymous donor gives a huge endowment.
條件就是 保持所有老展品不變…
With a proviso: Everything stays the same. So...
- 很明顯 也不是一點沒變 - 不是
- Well, not exactly the same, obviously. - No.
注意 女士們先生們 我是西奧多·羅斯福
Bully, lads and ladies, the name is Theodore Roosevelt,
一個自然主義者 又名狂野騎士 美國的第26任總統
naturalist, Rough Rider and twenty-sixth President of these great United States.
跟上 孩子 冒險開始 勞倫斯
Come along, lad. The hunt is afoot. Lawrence.
嘿 你們這些笨瓜給我帶口香糖嗎？
Hey, you dum-dums bring me gum-gum?
大約3000年前 我父母給了我這塊金牌
My parents gave me this tablet some 3,000 years ago,
這是埃及人民最至高無上的寶物
entrusting me with one of my people's most prized possessions.
- 它有什麼用？ - 什麼用？
- Does it do anything? - Do anything?
對 如果沒用的話要它來幹嘛？
Yeah. What's the point if it doesn't do anything?
告訴他們
Tell 'em
實際上 它是一塊復活金牌
Actually, it has a magical power
可以讓這堛漁i覽品都活過來
that brings all the exhibits to life.
好了 別開玩笑 它到底有什麼用？
No, really, what's it do?
沒用 只是裝飾品
Nothing. It's just for decoration.
我就知道
I knew it.
這媊窸z了 這個恐龍看上去一點都不真實
This place is lame. This thing doesn't even look real.
沒錯 老兄 這堛犒q動技術太落後了
Seriously, dude, these animatronics suck.
- 猛?象？ - 是啊
- Mammoth? - Yeah.
絕種了！
Extinct!
- 我已經跟不上科技發展了 - 是啊 做的像真的一樣
- Today's technology is beyond me. - I know. It's so lifelike.
- 是的 是的 - 問你件事
- Yeah, yeah, yeah. - Something else.
這次你打算做久一點
You'll stick around a bit longer this time,
還是像上次一樣幹了一半 又去幹別的？
or you gonna run away again when you get something better?
- 我會呆下去 - 一直呆下去？
- I'm gonna stay. - Stay, for a long time.
- 是的 - 是的
- Yeah. - Yeah.
很好 作為一個守衛 你…
Good. 'Cause, as night guards go, you're...
- 什麼？ - 是最棒的
- What? - The best.
我沒聽清
Excuse me.
你 小孩！不可以抱展覽品
You, the toddler! Don't hug the displays.
打擾了 你好
I'm sorry. Hi.
請原諒我的冒昧 我只是…
I don't mean to stare. I just...
你和我認識的一個人長得很像…
You look a lot like somebody I know, and...
很多人都這麼說
I get that a lot.
- 是嗎？ - 對 可能是我長了一張大眾臉吧
- Do you? - Yeah. I guess I have that kind of face.
- 大眾臉 - 是啊
- Familiar. - Yeah.
你不會碰巧和阿梅莉亞·埃爾哈特 有什麼親屬關係吧
You're not by any chance related to Amelia Earhart, are you?
- 沒有 - 沒有
- No. - No.
- 我想沒有 - 當然沒有
- No, I don't think so. - Of course you're not.
我是說 我不知道 也許我…
I mean, I don't know. Maybe I'm...
我只是忍不住想問 對不起
I just had to ask. I'm sorry.
她是那個第一個飛越太平洋的女性吧
She was that woman who flew across the Pacific.
- 大西洋 - 對 是大西洋
- The Atlantic. - Atlantic. Of course.
第一個飛越大西洋的女性 她還獲得過飛行十字勳章
First woman to fly across the Atlantic, and she received the Flying Cross,
女性當中也是第一個
first woman to do that.
- 真酷啊 - 對 她真的很酷
- That's very cool. - Yeah, she was cool.
你應該去微縮模型館看看
Hey, you know what you should check out is the the Hall of Miniatures.
你能給我帶路嗎？我總是迷路
Could you take me there? I'm always getting lost.
好的 當然 我來帶路 來吧
Yeah, I know. Sure. Yeah, I'll show you. Come on.
謝謝
Thank you.
- 我叫拉瑞·戴利 - 苔絲
- I'm Larry Daley. - Tess.
- 約瑟夫 吃晚飯了！ - 馬上來 媽媽
- Joseph, time for dinner! - One second, Ma!
喬伊·摩托羅拉 馬上給我下樓吃飯！
Joey Motorola, you get down here for supper right now!
我說了馬上來 媽 我正在研究一個很重要的東西
I said one second, Ma! I really think I'm on to something here!